<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rebellio debellata et Scotia rediviva, or, The downfall of rebellion and Scotlands resurrection, as it was represented in two sermons the one at Eccles last of May, the other preached at Jedburgh June 27, 1660, being both dayes set apart for solemn rejoycing and publike thanksgiving for the happy restauration of the king's most excellent Majesty to the exereise [sic] of his royall power / by Jo. Jameson minister at Eccles.</title>
            <author>Jameson, John, minister of Eccles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31158</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11781234</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11781234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1485:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rebellio debellata et Scotia rediviva, or, The downfall of rebellion and Scotlands resurrection, as it was represented in two sermons the one at Eccles last of May, the other preached at Jedburgh June 27, 1660, being both dayes set apart for solemn rejoycing and publike thanksgiving for the happy restauration of the king's most excellent Majesty to the exereise [sic] of his royall power / by Jo. Jameson minister at Eccles.</title>
                  <author>Jameson, John, minister of Eccles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by a Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Scotia rediviva, or Scotlands resurrection has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>REBELLIO DEBELLATA, ET SCOTIA REDIVIVA: OR The Downfall of Rebellion, and <hi>Scotlands</hi> Reſurrection,</p>
                  <p>As it was Repreſented in Two SERMONS: The one at <hi>ECCLES</hi> laſt of <hi>May,</hi> the other preached at <hi>JEDB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH</hi> June 27. 1660. Being both dayes ſet apart for Solemn Rejoycing and Publike Thankſgiving, for the happy Reſtauration of the KINGS moſt excellent Majeſty to the exereiſe of His Royall Power.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>JO. JAMESON</hi> Miniſter at <hi>ECCLES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>—<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p> 
                     <bibl>EPicharmus.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 7.16.</bibl>
                     <p>His miſchief ſhall return upon his own head, and his violent dealing ſhall come down upon his own pate.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 9.16.</bibl>
                     <p>The Lord is known by the judgement he exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth, the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by a Society of <hi>Stationers, Anno Dom.</hi> 1661.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:2"/>
                  <head>To the Right HONOURABLE And Noble Lord, JAMES Earle of <hi>Home,</hi> Lord <hi>Coldinghame,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Congregations of <hi>Eccles</hi> and <hi>Jedburgh</hi> for their conſtant Affection and Loyalty to the King, have been very eminent in their ſuffering, (as is well known to moſt that knows them) and both of them, through the happy return of the Kings Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, being fred from the fear of all ſuch barbarous violence and cruelty in time coming, and having deep impreſſions on their ſpirits of the ſuperlative
<pb facs="tcp:49068:3"/>advantage, that doth redound to all the Kings Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions thereby, did go about the duty of Publike Thanksgiving with much chearfulneſſe of heart. Having; as Paſtor to the one, and upon invitation (through the ſeekneſſe of their Miniſter) to the other, delivered a word of Congratulation, in the dayes ſet apart for that Work: This moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and unexpected Revolution, reſtoring His Majeſty ſo peaceably to the Thrones of His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Anceſtors, after ſuch earth-ſhaking intervals of time, after both His unparalelled and all good Subjects their long continued ſufferings, being a matter of ſuch profitable and univerſal influence, and ſo ſignal a token of Gods ſpecial mercy, as to theſe three Kingdoms in general; ſo to each Shire, City, Brugh, Incorporation, Paroch, Village, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, Perſon (whither of high or low degree) in particular, and that not only in this preſent, but in all ſubſequent and ſucceeding generations; I found my ſelf bound in conſcience, according to the ſmall meaſure of gifts diſpenſed unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e, to lay before them that which I thought both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them as good Chriſtians and Loyal Subjects, which now the importunity of ſeveral of them conſtraineth me to make publike, and expoſe to the cenſure of theſe critical times.</p>
                  <p>My Noble Lord, as your Lordſhip knoweth me to be none of the moſt preſumptuous, ſo am I ſufficiently convinced of my own weakneſſe, and thereupon very ſenſible how much need I have to
<pb facs="tcp:49068:3"/>take Sanctuary under the umbradge of ſome Noble Patron; and hence it is from a long ſeries of experiences, which I have had of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips reſpects in the blackeſt and moſt diſmall of times (as all others likewiſe who were in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering condition for their duty to God, and loyalty to their King) I am encouraged (ſince Epiſtling is come in cuſtome) in all humility, to offer unto your Lordſhip thoſe inſuing Sermons: that coming abroad under the conduct of ſo Great and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Name, they may find the better acceptance amongſt all candid and loyall perſons: which as your Lordſhips many favours and reiterated obligations, may juſtly challenge from my hands as a debt, ſo alſo do I tender with all dutiful and humble reſpect. Your Lordſhip hath the teſtimony of a conſtant friend to your Mother-Church, in the day of her trouble and affliction: and indeed, had you not ſtood in the way to mens deſigns, the Church of God in our bounds had been drowned in a Sea of Confuſion, and Speat of Cruelty, and this is a great badge of Honor, far beyond that of Nobility of Blood, and all the ſhort lived Trophees of time. Although this ſtorm be over, it is the expectation of all good men, that your Lordſhips care and tender affection ſhall notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding continue, which will encourage them to be earneſt ſupplicants to God for long laſting and continual proſperity to your Houſe: the powring down of the riches of His bleſſing on your Self,
<pb facs="tcp:49068:4"/>Honourable Lady, and all the Hopefull and Noble Stems of your Ancient Family: that you and they may be ſtill crowned with bayes of Honour here, and eternity of Happineſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, which ſhall ever be the fervent prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips humble ſervant in the Lord, <hi>JO JAMESON.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                        <date>Jan. 26. 1661.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:4"/>
                  <head>REBELLIO DEBELLATA, OR The Downfall of Rebellion.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>Iſa. 1.25.</bibl> I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy droſs, and take-away all thy tinne.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>26.</bibl> I will reſtore thy Judges as at firſt, and thy Counſellours as at the beginning.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen perſonall Reformation and National Reſtauration meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the encounter is much like <hi>Jacobs</hi> with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with reciprocal joy and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual advantage, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> fed <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſed <hi>Joſeph;</hi> ſo the Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Civil Government, proveth a Bulwark to Piety, and Holineſſe a wreath of bleſſings to reſtored Government: You have theſe two twiſted together in this Text by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, I wiſh they tryſte together in theſe times in our performance. In the Verſes preceeding, the Prophet hath levelled many ſharp threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings at <hi>Judah,</hi> in theſe two, to the remnant that ſhall eſcape from the execution of theſe terrible woes denounced there, he preſenteth a cordial of ſingular value, that thereby he may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49068:5"/>reſuſcitate their languiſhing ſpirits, hopeleſſe of any deliverance, and eſtranged to all comfort. If you would conſider the words ſeriouſly, it will appear they contian a gracious revolution of Divine Providence: the ſun of their proſperity, which had been long under a ſad eclipſe, ariſeth here with beautiful &amp; refreſhing rayes, elevating their joy to the higheſt pitch, <hi>Ile turn my hand upon thee, &amp;c.</hi> And you may take them aſunder in theſe two: 1. An happy change. 2. The happy conſequences of the change; or if you will, an happy change, and the happy parts and branches thereof. The happy change, <hi>Ile turn my hand upon thee:</hi> We have ſeen many viciſſitudes and unhappy changes of late, making our ears to tingle, and our hearts to tremble, which hath diſcovered to us many hollow-hearted change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: Now both this Text and Time giveth us occaſion to hear and treat of <hi>(Rara avis in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris)</hi> a bleſſed and happy change, a change though ſome never expected, yet many longed earneſtly to behold, and now by the goodneſſe of our God, have gotten occaſion with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. to cry out, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</hi> If the Quere be moved, what is meant by <hi>hand?</hi> It is anſwered, the Prophet ſpeaketh <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> after the manner of men, yet it is to be undrſtood <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> according as it will quadrate and agree with the perfection of God; for God hath no
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49068:5"/>hands, nor feet, as the <hi>Anthropomorphits</hi> fondly did imagine: ſo that by <hi>(hand)</hi> is underſtood the power of God, in the exerciſe of which Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and Inſtrument, the power of man both doth appear, and is repreſented. Gods power and hand in Scripture, ſometimes is taken for His punitive Juſtice, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Job</hi> 13.21. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is taken for his preſerving Mercy and delivering power from evil, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.11. It is this laſt acceptation here it goeth under, As if God had ſaid, I will put no longer out my power to puniſh you for your ſins, but will turn it into another channel for thy Reſtauration and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up: Which affordeth to us this <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God doth not alwayes keep his Church in the furnace of affliction, but alloweth them times of Releaſe and Deliverance: He doth not alwayes chide ſaith the Pſalmiſt, nor keep his anger for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. He is not worſe to his Saints, nor he willed them to be to their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, He commanded to grant unto them their years of Jubile, and can it be poſſible that he will deny unto his Church her times of Joy, He hath given to her times of Jubile and ſolemn Manumiſſion from her Oppreſſors, changing her aſhes unto beauty, and making the bones broken to rejoyce, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. What was Chriſts lote in his death, is the Churches in this life, he carried his croſſe a while, and then he was eaſed by <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> of <hi>Serene:</hi> The Church may be under a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49068:6"/>heavy burden of calamity, but he will not let it reſt upon her lote, leſt his people put forth their hand unto iniquity; which ſtream if we ſhould follow up to its ſource, we will find it billowing out from the fountain of Gods love, and no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Churches merit: It is upon this ſcore we are to reckon all the favours that we have of late received in this Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, yea, the Church Triumphant as to her glorious attainments, ſpeaketh in no other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and hereupon we ought to go out to meet the Lord with praiſe, who hath compaſſed us about with ſongs of deliverance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.7. And ſince he cometh out to us with changed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of providence, let us meet him with changed diſpoſitions of heart; have we not good reaſon ſo to do, ſince the three bitter cups, 1. Of aſtoniſhment and deſolation: 2. The cup of fury: 3. The cup of trembling, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.17. which we have been drinking of theſe many years, are changed unto three joyful cups, the cup of Bleſſing, the cup of Conſolation, the cup of Salvation, uſed frequently among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and this day put morally in our hands: 1. The cup of Bleſſing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. which was uſed by the <hi>Jews</hi> at their ſolemn Feaſts, ſo called, becauſe of theſe Bleſſings and Thankſgivings annexed. We have this put in our hands this day, having in our Kings return received many Bleſſings, and ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49068:6"/>there is required much Bleſſing and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from us, which if we pay, we make uſe of this cup: let us not forget thus to drink libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, for there is no fear of exceſſe thereby. The ſecond cup was the cup of Conſolation, uſed by friends in time of mourning, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 7. to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate their ſorrow, and refreſh their ſpirits, and this alſo is preſented to us in the return of our gracious King; for, was not loyal and faithful hearts mourning for three dead Kingdoms, the death of a pious and wiſe King, and the affliction of his Royal Succeſſor? now here they have all conſolation, both as to the reſurrection of three Kingdoms, the condign puniſhment of unpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelled parricids, and the following glory and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to his preſent Majeſty. The third cup is the cup of Salvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.13. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients after ſignal deliverances, uſed firſt to offer Sacrifices, and thereafter to have ſolemn Feaſts, at which they rejoyced in God, and moderatly (but yet chearfully) made uſe of the creatures: after which they had a cup, which every one lifted up as they drank, and this was called the cup of Salvation; for hereby they teſtified how highly their hearts were lifted up to God in the ſenſe of their deliverance from their enemies, and the miſeries under which by them they were born down: This alſo is given to us this day; for we have received ſalvation from our enemies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from our oppreſſors, and ſo have good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49068:7"/>reaſon morally to lift up our hearts to God in the ſenſe of his goodneſſe, as they did this cup ceremonially, even with ſpiritual rejoyceing in his Name.</p>
                  <p>Thus we have ſhortly ſpoke to the change, now we come to the branches, or if you will, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof: The firſt is, <hi>I will purely purge away all thy droſſe, and take away all thy tinne:</hi> The ſecond is, And <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt holdeth out the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ablatum,</hi> the evil that is removed: The ſecond, the <hi>bonum collatum,</hi> the good that is reſtored. For the firſt, It holdeth out the evil that is to be removed, what this was, it will not be amiſſe that we make ſome enquiry; Some think it only to be the grown of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanity and looſeneſſe of life, and the creeping in of Idolatry and Hypocrifie, expreſſed here by the names of <hi>(droſſe)</hi> and <hi>(tinne)</hi> others think the evil thus expreſſed, includeth with theſe ſins, the unlawful, wicked and uſurped Power lifted up over them; the time of which may fitly be referred to the dayes that <hi>Senache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib</hi> came up againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.13. who took many of their fenced cities; or els to the time of <hi>Achaz</hi> (for <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſied in the reign of both theſe Kings) when the Kingdom was under the feet of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. Theſe forementioned ſins being the effects of the bad Government of theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49068:7"/>unfaithful Rulers, following als naturally there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as the inferior Sphears do the motion of the firſt mover: The <hi>Dutch</hi> Notes favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this interpretation, and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> upon the place hath alſo a hint thereat, which I incline to follow, thinking it a ſpiritual thrift to joyne ſuch Interpretations as do not juſle one with another, and ſhall accordingly handle the words, but ſhall firſt ſpeak to the removing of the <hi>uſurping external,</hi> and then to the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>uſurping internal power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the firſt, The removing of the external uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping power, <hi>I will purely purge away thy droſſe, and take away all thy tinne:</hi> Here be three things wrapped up, 1. What is to be removed, <hi>Thy droſſe and all thy tinne,</hi> theſe two expreſſions point at two ſeveral kinds of their preſent Rulers: The firſt of which decyphering ſuch who had neither title nor qualification for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſome of their off-ſcourings who did aſſociat with the Invaders, or els ſome of theſe who did invade and wanted ſails for ſuch a bottome as they imbarked into, theſe were ſimply unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and als uſeleſſe for the Commonwealth, as droſſe to a Gold-ſmith. The ſecond delineateth another kind and generation of them who had accompliſhment and parts, but no juſt title to the office of Magiſtracy, their qualification giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them a ſhow, but their cruelty and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion both in attaining and retaining the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49068:8"/>ſame, making them to differ als far from the true Magiſtrate, as Tinne from Silver and Gold: theſe are comparatively unprofitable, and more burdenſome in their little finger, then the righteous Ruler in his loyns. Whence theſe two Propoſitions may be gathered: Firſt, Sometimes the baſeſt of men climb up to the exerciſe of Government: Secondly, Such ſort of Rulers are moſt unprofitable to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sometimes the baſeſt of men climb up to the exerciſe of Government; did not <hi>Abimelech</hi> that Bramble, come to be Lord and Lawgiver to all his Brethren, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9? And <hi>Zimri</hi> that King-killing monſter (though his time of enjoyment thereof was ſhort) to the Throne of his Maſter? <hi>Athenion,</hi> a man of no great extract, arriveth at the Government of the famous City of <hi>Athens: Jack Cade</hi> had no worſe ſucceſſe, who aſſociating with Birds of his own feather, proveth like the Dragon in the <hi>Revel.</hi> with this difference, that whil'ſt the one draweth Stars from Heaven with his tail, the other draweth his aſſociats to be ſtars in the heaven of Magiſtracy, Yeſterday, <hi>Muſhromes</hi> and <hi>Peeces</hi> of moſt uſeleſſe droſſe, from the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy dung-hill of obſcurity and baſeneſſe, though they proved but meteors and of no long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. And it is no wonder it falleth thus out, if you will look unto the ladder by which they mount up to this pinnacle: the firſt ſtep of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49068:8"/>which is a great pretence for the liberty of the Subject, raiſing Hew and Cry as if ſome had ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len this from the people, whereas none but themſelves have ſuch a deſign: This great Thief and Mountybank imitateth the pitty Thief his younger Brother, who cutteth his neighbours purſe, and then cryeth out with the firſt, hold the Thief; bewitching ſo the people, that with <hi>Eſops</hi> Dog, they grip at the ſhaddow of Liberty, and lets the ſubſtance ſlip: many people being ſo fick of a feveriſh credulity, that they promiſe to themſelves in new Magiſtrates, mountains of commodity, dreaming in their change, to fall on ſuch a Maſter as the King of <hi>Moroco</hi> promiſeth to be to his Subject, one that will do juſtice to all men, make the Sun to ſhine, and the Clouds to rain, and the Earth to prove fruitful.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſtep is, The winding of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as the Serpent did himſelf into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe) into ſuch a degree of Military com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as may fit them for ſome State pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy, and the moulding of all Affairs, according to the patern of their own pleaſure: The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God giveth the Sword to thoſe that have the right to judge, moſt clearly in Scripture; but they think the right to judge, belongeth to theſe who have the Sword, coercive and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, they make the conſtituent the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God the conſequent of Magiſtracy, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49068:9"/>this is not the firſt lie that they have given to the Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p>The third ſtep is, Making uſe of that Sword-power, to the impoveriſhing of all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, chaſtiſing them by this rod of Iron, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by eating up like a moath their Eſtates, and as a Horſe-leach ſouking out the blood and vitals of their Fortunes, do cruelly make them <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours for a word,</hi> and put their tongues in the ſtocks, and their perſons in priſon, that they may captivate their ſpirits to deſpondency, or by breaking their hearts, cauſe them to mend their pace to eternity.</p>
                  <p>The fourth ſtep is, The ſecret underminding of the honour and credit of thoſe, whoſe ſtudy it was to ſtand in the way of their rebellious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; as <hi>Abſolom</hi> did with his Royal Father: and if theſe be ſo blameleſſe, as they can have no true and juſt ground to render them odious from, by a devote artifice, they can charge them with crimes (as being enemies to Religion and the power of Godlineſſe) of which themſelves are guilty in an eminent manner.</p>
                  <p>The fifth ſtep of this ladder is, The making uſe of ſome Spiritual Heraulds (ſo <hi>Adonijah</hi> did with <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.7.) to denounce wrath and judgement againſt all the oppoſits: And like <hi>Achabs</hi> falſe prophets, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phefie ſucceſſe and honour to them, ſending their rebellions deſigns abroad to the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49068:9"/>of the vulgar, under the impreſſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, theſe not being ſo foreſeeing as to remember <hi>omne malum incipit in nomine domini,</hi> that all wicked deſigns are covered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fair pretences of Godlineſſe. And if theſe uſurping heads intend the extenſion of that power, to procure among thoſe, they are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade ſome of the ſame Coat to pull a coal from the Altar; to put both Church and State in a fire, that ſo they may eat the fruits of that maxime of <hi>Machiavil, divide &amp; impera,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and reign.</p>
                  <p>The ſixth ſtep is perjury, Looking upon Oaths and Vows as <hi>pias fraudes,</hi> holy ingines, and theſe like a ſleep-pillow they put under peoples heads to lull them faſt aſleep, that they may neither ſee their projects, nor fear their power, of which they make as frequent uſe, as the thief of his artificial lantern, by which he beholdeth others, and paſſeth unſeen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  <p>The ſeventh ſtep is, Blaſphemy againſt the Kings Majeſty; for having blaſphemed the Name of God, it followeth, that they blaſpheme the King, Gods Vicegerent: Theſe two like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> marcheth together in others hands; it ſeemeth they have no purpoſe (though out of no reſpect to him) that <hi>Jude</hi> ſhould be a falſe prophet, who foretelleth, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. That in the latter times, there ſhall be a generation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49068:10"/>who delight to ſpeak evil of Dignities: But though <hi>Jude</hi> fortelleth this, yet he approveth it not: for the ſame Spirit <hi>Jude</hi> ſpoke by, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. joyneth theſe two together, <hi>Fear God and honour the King:</hi> And, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. It is expreſly forbidden, <hi>Thou ſhall not revile the Gods,</hi> (that is the Magiſtrate) <hi>nor curſe the ruler of thy people,</hi> and avouched to be a high contempt of Gods ſelf, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8 7.</p>
                  <p>The laſt ſtep is blood, Even the blood of Kings, King-killing, which in all ages hath been looked upon (except among the Jeſuites) as the higheſt of villanies; this they can go about and perpetrate with the boldeſt countenance that ever any thing was acted. The light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture taught the heathen, that blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was a great pollution, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, pollute not thy hands with blood, much more the ſhedding of the blood of Kings, is of that nature. <hi>Xiphilinus</hi> determineth, it was not competent for Subjects to judge them, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, it is to God alone the judging of Princes belong: far leſſe is it for Subjects to kill them, <hi>Reges in ipſos imperium eſt Jovis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. We may behold, hence, that it is no wonder that ſuch come up unto the batlements of Government, ſince they climb by ſuch a ſtair: men that will extinguiſh the light of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience within, and draw a skryne betwixt it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49068:10"/>and any light, the ſun of Divine Truth in Gods Word doth communicate from without, being like the unjuſt Judge, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. neither fearing God nor reverencing man: what great things of time may they not reach and attaine unto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It is als little wonder to ſee them fall trimbling down, like <hi>Phaeton</hi> in the fable, kicked out of the Chair of that Chariot they were driving, and made a ludibry and mocking-ſtock to all the world about, <hi>For thy violence againſt thy brother Jacob, ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever,</hi> Obad. 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Beware of medling with things too high for thee; <hi>Solomons</hi> counſel is good, medle not with theſe that are given to change. Theſe will be Gods on earth: and while they are climbing to taſte of this forbidden fruit, they are falling down to the ſociety of the devils in hell, they are externally aſcending, but ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcending: they muſt have eſteem among men, and in the mean while, they loſſe their eſteem with God. This climbing (to their ſmall ſatisfaction) maketh them climb another ladder where they reap neither the fruit of honour nor profit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. Invaders and Uſurpers of Magiſtracy, are unprofitable for the Commonwealth, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then droſſe and time to the Goldſmith, of which he can make no Jewel nor precious Veſſel;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49068:11"/>whither theſe be both without Title and Parts, or have Parts and want Title: a Gold-ring can never be made of tinne, more nor of droſſe: What profit had <hi>Shechem</hi> by <hi>Abimelech,</hi> Judg. 9.57. <hi>And all the evil of the men of Shechem did God render upon their heads: and upon them came the curſe of Jotham the ſon of Jerubbaal:</hi> no, they are ſo far from being profitable, that they are a very burden, proving like an unfaithful ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard to his maſter, ſquizing his tennants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pity or compaſſion; or like to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Task-maſters, whoſe oppreſſion imbittered the lives of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea more, they are a very plague, and one of theſe terrible plagues the Lord ſmote <hi>Egypt</hi> with, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.34. <hi>He ſent locuſts and caterpillers that deſtroyed all the hearbs, and eat up all the fruits of the land:</hi> Indeed ſuch are locuſts to that Kingdom they bring under their power: they and their ſupporters deſtroying all the fruits of the land, their purſes being as empty of Money, as their perſons are of worth, the people to make them up, muſt pull themſelves down, and is not this to be unprofitable in a ſingular manner?</p>
                  <p>The reaſons of this are: Firſt, Theſe are men utterly void of a publike ſpirit, having their own greatneſſe, not the peoples good before their eyes, and it is impoſſible that it can be otherwiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when this is made the mark at which all their endeavours are levelled.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49068:11"/>
                  <p>Secondly, Such are without all ſympathic and fellow-feeling of peoples diſtreſſe and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not being the kindly parent, <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> but like the unnatural Mother in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, cruel as Tigars, and ſo their adminiſtrations can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not not but be very far from bringing in any profit to a Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, It cometh to paſſe on this account, becauſe they are void of conſcience; for they reſolve to throw this aſide, as the main <hi>remora</hi> to great atchievments, and leaſt their impiety ſhould become palpable, they do it neatly, even under the pretence of a moſt tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, They are thus unprofitable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are men void of all honour; he that maketh <hi>proprium commodum ſupremam legem,</hi> his own advantage the Supream Law, can never be a man of honourable principles; and one that acts not from ſuch, will never be inſtrumental to do good to a Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, All their ſupporters are of the ſame ſtamp; for it may be ſaid of them as God ſaid of the makers and worſhippers of Idols, <hi>That they who make them be like unto them, and ſo are all they that truſt in them:</hi> Hence both great and ſmall of them become birds of prey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Here is a true character of theſe that raviſh Magiſtracy, and as by a glaſſe their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49068:12"/>complexion is repreſented; however, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe great things to the deluded people, and flatters them with a hope of heaven upon earth, under the ſhaddow of their power; yet they are like <hi>Joah</hi> to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> kiſſing and imbracing, that they may the more covertly cut them off; doing as thoſe who mannage young horſes, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and wiſely handle them, till once they be in the ſadle, and then they ride them as they pleaſe, and make them give obedience to their cruel commands, or elſe to reſolve to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in utter ruine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. How good reaſon have we to bleſſe God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> laſt, who hath freed us of this woful generation, that as we read of ſome Cats, who have been found ſtanding over chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with their mouths to theirs, ſouking thence their breath, were ſtanding over all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of people in this Land! and if God had not in time prevented them, they had made us a moſt miſerable people; no, they had cut us off from having a Name among the Nations; and ſo much the higher ſhould our rejoyceing ariſe, that we ſee in their filthy advantage and unjuſt gain, they have met with ſignal diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it proving as the airly dew: and the ſweetnes and contentment which they found in our ruines, nothing but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a falſe ſweetneſſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them vomiting up their morſels, which cruelly and greedily they had devoured.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49068:12"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Let us pray to God to bleſſe him and them who were the inſtruments in Gods hand of this happy Revolution: that man of Valour who lately commanded in this Land, and thoſe of our Nobles, Gentry and Paſtors, that animated and encouraged him unto the work, being unto him (under many ſad diſcouragements he met with) as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> holding up his heart as thoſe did <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands. The good will of him that dwelt in the Buſh, be toward them all; for they have ſweeped to the door of theſe Kingdomes, the droſſe and tinne of Uſurpers: it was God that guided them in every ſtep, for they walked in the midſt of hazards. The Jewiſh Rabbins have a fancy, that the miſreading one letter in the words, <hi>Ein Kadoſh Caihovah, Beth,</hi> to wit, for <hi>Caph</hi> in JEHOVAH, deſtroyeth the world. Truely the miſplacing one ſtep of him and them, had deſtroyed the whole world of our comfort: that Lord who guided them then, guide them all ſtill! till, as they have brought theſe Lands to the enjoying of peace and proſperity, they themſelves may be brought to the enjoying of eternal felicity.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond thing in the words, is, The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mover, He who purgeth out the droſſe and the tinne from among them: Its <hi>(I)</hi> that is God, it is He that layeth the Axe of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the root of the Bramble; no leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Omnipotency, and there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49068:13"/>is no let to the doing thereof, when Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency is ſtreached out.</p>
                  <p>The third thing, is, The manner how this is done, that is expreſſed in the words <hi>purely purge;</hi> and becauſe the word <hi>Tſaraſh,</hi> tranſlated to purge, ſignifieth to melt or burn out: I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to think that the Alluſion here, is made to the purging by fire, it being a word proper to Goldſmiths, and that the Nown is included in the Verb, <hi>I will purge with fire purely;</hi> or as it is in the Marginals of ſome Bibles, <hi>I will purge you according to pureneſſe,</hi> which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be pureneſſe of fire, and in this I follow the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Annotations on the place. If the Quere be moved, What is meant by this fire? I anſwer, It is Gods indignation and anger which is very fitly repreſented by, and reſembled to fire upon many accounts; but eſpecially, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its penetrating nature, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.14. and becauſe of its deſtroying nature, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.16. For as fire penetrateth and runneth through the Mettal in a ſearching way, and deſtroyeth that which is combuſtible when it ſeazeth upon the ſame, ſo can Gods anger pierce in unto the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt combinations, and alſo deſtroy them. Then you have here firſt the manner of removing of theſe as to man, which is with difficulty and hardſhip; for the removing of droſſe by melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is no eaſie task. And, ſecondly, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as to God, and that is by the fire of His
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49068:13"/>anger. Hence from theſe two, the removing and the manner of the removing of theſe evils thus explained to you: I offer theſe three <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. It is very difficult to get the droſſe of Uſurpation purged out of a Land.</item>
                     <item>2. For as difficult as it is, God can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it.</item>
                     <item>3. God in his performing hereof, pulleth down Uſurpers in his indignation and anger.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. It is a very difficult work the purge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Uſurpation from a Kingdom: What blood was ſhed? what pains was ſpent? what time paſt ere <hi>Abimelech</hi> was brought down from his greatneſſe? And wrs the overturning of <hi>Athaliah</hi> any eaſier task? Did ſhe not keep the Chair ſix years in deſpight of all the Loyal and Royal Party of <hi>Judah?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The reaſons why this is ſo hard a task, and men meet with ſuch difficulties therein: Are firſt, the general impenitency of all ſorts and degrees of people, they taking the boldneſſe to ſin with a high hand againſt God, and wilfully refuſing to turn from the evil of their way; God doth in juſtice continue upon people the yoke of Uſurpation; becauſe they will not take upon them the yoke of his ſubjection.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond reaſon is from the cruelty of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, they doing with all men of power and parts that will not bow down to worſhip their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49068:14"/>Dagon, as the Patriarchs did with <hi>Joſeph;</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, ſelling, impriſoning them: yea worſe, beheading them, leſt one time or another, they might have watched an opportunity to bring in the Government to run in its right and old channel.</p>
                  <p>The third reaſon is from their falſeneſſe. <hi>Matchavel,</hi> no, the devil himſelf is hardly more a cheat, then ſome Uſurpers have been, having ſuch a faculty of bewitching ſimple ones, to the belief of their Saintſhip, by a devote de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uchng of themſelves (to peoples apprehenſion) and taking upon them the guilt of much ſin; for which they declared themſelves (as indeed they had reaſon) not worthy the name of Chriſtians, that their groſſeſt facts being thus tinctured with ſuch extraordinary profeſſions of humility and holineſſe, were ſwallowed down by people without any further enquiry; ſo that they cheated the people in telling unto them the very truth.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, This cometh to paſſe through the treachery of many, who becoming eyes to the Uſurpers, as to the diſcovery of any deſigns againſt them, were made uſe of by them as ſo many Beagles, to hunt out and diſcover all theſe who had any inclination to overturn their power, keeping them into a chain of Gold; and as they had information, ſending them abroad to all Comers, to all Countries, yea, even to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49068:14"/>Family of the righteous Heir: <hi>A mans enemies,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>may be theſe of his own houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Becauſe of the baſeneſſe of the Rich, and thoſe on whom God hath beſtowed great things, who make their worldly concernments and Eſtates their God, laying down this baſe principle to <hi>ſtand with all, and fall with none,</hi> ſo that with <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> they couch under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Uſurpation, and rather then they ſhould undergo any hardſhip, they will ſuffer Religion to loſſe its ſplendor, the King his Crown, their Country her Honour.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Becauſe of the diligence of Upſtarts, who in their Countries ruine, purchaſed to themſelves great Means and Eſtates: who that they may not loſſe that which they have moſt unlawfully gote, diligently take all wayes, and uſe all means, <hi>per fas &amp; nefas,</hi> to ſupport the Bramble, under whoſe ſhroude they have ſo well proſpered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This informeth us why theſe three Kingdoms have theſe many years groaned under Uſurpation, it being ſo hard and difficult a work to pull it down, ſince there was ſo much of impenitency in the Nations, ſo great cruelty and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ep cunning in the Uſurpers, ſo much treachery among the poor, ſuch baſeneſſe of ſpirit among the Rich, ſuch diligence among Muſhromes, produced by the influence of that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49068:15"/>prodigious Comet, that was Gods <hi>Attila</hi> to theſe Lands of late; we have far better reaſon to admire that our deliverance was ſo ſoon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, than that it was ſo long deferred.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Hence we may ſee what ſenſe we ſhould have of our deliverance; the greater difficulty that hath been therein, the greater degree of ſenſe thereof ſhould be unto us: The ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the pangs that the mother hath in childe-birth, maketh her when ſhe is delivered from torment, the more highly to account, and thankfully to remember of her coming back to her wonted health: Exquiſit hath been the pangs of theſe three Kingdoms, eſpecially of this, in the attempting that which now we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; <hi>The childe having been brought to the birth, and there being no ſtrength to bring forth,</hi> which calleth unto us, to value the ſame at the higheſt rate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. Though Uſurpation be not eaſily pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down, yet the hand of Omnipotency can daſh it in pieces: <hi>Shall the Lyon roar, and the beaſts of the Forreſts not trimble?</hi> Aſſerteth not God this for his prerogative, to pull down one, and ſet up another? Hath not He in His hand a full cup, whereof He can make the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt drink? <hi>Though thou mount up with the Eagles, and build thy neſt with the Stars, yet I will bring thee down, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Obad. 1.4. How ſoon can he turn the wheel of Providence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49068:15"/>upſide down, and take the greateſt <hi>Anakim</hi> of policy, in the thicket of his own projects: and when he would hide himſelf from God and Man under the ſhade of his own contrivances, the Lord can bring him out as he did <hi>Adam,</hi> conſcious of his wickedneſſe, and make him fall into the ditch he hath digged for others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.15. <hi>His miſchief returning upon his own head, and his violent dealing on his owne pate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. For reproof, How juſtly may I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an unbelieving generation, who expunged this truth out of their Creed? many being amongſt us like <hi>Jorams</hi> favorite, on whoſe ſhoulder he did lean, when the lepers brought the good news to <hi>Samaria</hi> of the flying of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.17. ſuppoſing this Babel of unrighteouſneſſe could never be pulled down, which made them both ſo forgetful of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the King, and ſo forward in devoting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Uſurpers, becoming an Echo to all their unjuſt commands, and the inſtruments of many of their barbarous cruelties, cleaving as faſt to them as theſe ſhepheards, who firſt found out the Loadſtone did to the rock thereof: never thinking there would be a day of reckoning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, and putting far of the great reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Tribunal of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Let us exalt the Name of him whoſe right hand is a hand of power, and doth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49068:16"/>he will, both in the heavens and in the earth: This day is a day of Thankſgiving and Praiſe, and when every point we meet with do give us occaſion to enter upon the duty of the Day, we were much to blame if we ſhould be deficient herein. We have good reaſon to bleſſe the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that hath confirmed to us this Truth, which was almoſt, as many other Truths (in theſe Truth loathing times) periſhed as to peoples acknowledging thereof: And in doing of this, as he proclaimed to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> all his holy Attributes in paſſing by before him; ſo to us moſt evidently two of them, his Wiſdom and Juſtice; his Wiſdom, in that he hath made their fall ſo like to the fall of <hi>Herod, Act.</hi> 12. who was eaten up with wormes that came out of his own bowels; for by the vermine of the Army, through the proweſſe of their General, bred in the bowels of their politick contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, are they eaten up and overthrown. His Juſtice, that made that Army whom they had Inſtrumented in the oppreſſing, ruinating, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of many, turn upon themſelves, as the Elephants did of old in many Battels, upon their own, and overturn them utterly. This calleth both for our Admiration and our Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. God in performing hereof, pulleth down Uſurpers in his anger and indignation, <hi>Jud.</hi> 9.53. Thus <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who revolted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49068:16"/>from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> his poſterity is rooted out, and not one to piſſe againſt the wall is left undeſtroyed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.29. And <hi>Zimri</hi> who killed his Maſter, had not long peace, till the vengeance of the Lord ſeized on him. God is angry with ſuch wicked ones every day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.11. Although providence do ſeem to dandle them, carrying them up in the armes of ſucceſſe for a time; yet even then the Lord his anger is againſt them, but it is like a myne of Powder, the Train burning ſome hours in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret before it come to the height, and then breaking out to the aſtoniſhment of behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                  <p>And his anger in pulling down of them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in theſe ſeveral particulars.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, In the publikeneſſe thereof, it is in the view and obſervation of all the Kingdoms and Nations about: theſe Uſurpers being brought upon a Theatre before them, and they fitting, as it were, on benches looking on, God having called them as in <hi>Joel</hi> 3.12. He calleth upon the nations to gather themſelves, <hi>for that he is to caſt down the mighty</hi> (ſo is it in the old Tranſlation) <hi>and to ſit himſelf as Judge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, His anger in their fall appeareth in the non-expectedneſſe thereof, when with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> they are ſoaring upon the wings of applauſe, and in popular acclamations, called and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pitty Gods; and they ſuppoſing to have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49068:17"/>good ground of promiſing to themſelves, that their mountain ſhall ſtand ſtrong: even then it is, that he can and doth, throw both the horſe and his rider into the ſea of confuſion, and utter ruine, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, It appeareth from the ſhamefulneſſe of their fall; for it is not ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but to the loweſt ſtep of indignity and diſgrace, and that without regrate or pity; yea, with the joy and rejoyceing of all that are not partakers of their guiltineſſe, the Lord throwing ſhameful ſpewing on all their evil pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed glory, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, It appeareth in the terribleneſſe thereof, their fall carrying with Them all their ſupporters and props, root and branch, puteth them in <hi>Adonijahs</hi> and his fellow-conſpirators their poſture, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1. to flee here and there, not knowing where to lay their head; it coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them like another day of Judgement, that they know not where to get a mountain under whoſe ſhaddow they may lurk, and hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the ſtroak their impious courſes hath deſerved.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Gods anger appeareth in the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitants of this fall, which is ſearching out and bringing to light the hidden windings of their ſinful wayes, by pulling off that mask, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did palliate their villanies, under which they have long walked; beſide the candle God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49068:17"/>lighteth in their own boſomes, their awakened conſciences, which muſtereth up before them all their rebellious and ſinful acts of violence and oppreſſion: The Lord lighteth another candle, His own wiſe providence, which ſtrangely brings to remembrance, and preſenteth to the eye of the world, that which they thought in their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to have buried in forgetfulneſſe, even their hidden things of diſhoneſty and diſloyalty, Hab. 2.17. <hi>The violence of Lebanon ſhall cover thee,</hi> It being as impoſſible for them to cover their violence, as it was for <hi>Lebanon</hi> to cover hers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Behold here a Scheme of the late tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling down of that <hi>Babel,</hi> which was founded on blood, and builded with blaſphemies; hath not the Lord, as with a Sun-beam, written His diſpleaſure upon the builders, and diſcovered his anger in their ruine? ſo publike is it, that the eyes of the nations are fixed thereon with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration; ſo unexpected, that immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as before the breaking of day, the night falls darkeſt) the worſt of evils were imminent, both State concuſſions and Church confuſions, and theſe who did firſt ſhape that Monſter-<hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> were ready to ſet it upon a ſurer foundation then before; ſo ſhameful, that he who aſſumed to himſelf the Title of <hi>Highneſs,</hi> is thrown down to the Abyſſe of <hi>Lowneſs:</hi> and that <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> which was the water of which this Yce
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49068:18"/>did Coagulate, and in which it Thawed again, is now quite exhaled by the Beams of the Royal Sun: So terrible, that their potent Allies abroad, dare not make mention of their Names, but with Apologies in their mouths: and their ſupporters at home are flying, being purſued with their own evil conſciences out of this world by <hi>poſterns</hi> of their own making: Whil'ſt others are juſtly to be hailed to the Gallows to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat their villanies with the beſt of their blood: And ſo powerfull is the ſearching that attendeth on it, that you may diſcover them by their countenances, their countenances being als falſe to their conſciences, as their conſciences had been to their King and Country: As the day it diſcovereth the thief, ſo our Deliverance doth theſe, and calleth aloud, <hi>Behold the man that made not God, but lies his refuge.</hi> If we ſhall ſearch how this ruine came upon them, we muſt caſt an eye both upon the fewel of Gods wrath among them, and upon the friends that appeared for us. The fewel amongſt them was their own ſins, none being ſo great enemies to their ſtanding as themſelves, like <hi>Jeroboam</hi> who founded the greatneſſe of his family by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, and ruined the ſame by his provocations; the ſins that kindled the Lords anger againſt theſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and hailed down vengeance on their heads, Were, firſt, Their powring out, as water on the ground, the Royal Blood of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49068:18"/>Lords Anointed<note n="*" place="margin">Quo nulla dudum ſplendidior, malo illuxit orbi, lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas, &amp; in polo non ſidus ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum puriore lumine coeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colis renidet.</note>, without regard to his Sacred Perſon, brinding him in the noontide of the day, moſt barbarouſly to the place of Execution, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gates of his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and in the view of his Subjects, ſeparated the Head of the Head of three Kingdoms from his Shoulders; a fact without all parallel, and to be remembred with continual lamentation, as to his loſſe, and with everlaſting deteſtation of their horrid cruelty, this cryed aloud: <hi>Wo to him that buildeth a town with bloud,</hi> Hab. 2.12. <hi>The Lord will abhor the bloudy and deceitful man,</hi> pſal. 5.6. Secondly, The baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Royal Family, by which they were keeped long under the preſſour of many afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, others impudently &amp; inſolently poſſeſſing that which was their Birth-right: This cryed aloud for vengeance in the words of <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.6.11. <hi>Wo to him that increaſeth that which is not his, and inlargeth his deſire as hell: For the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber ſhall anſwer it:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Exurge vindex, &amp; rubente</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sacrilegos jaculare dextra.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>And no wonder the voice hereof was loud, ſince their ſufferings were ſo ſingular. Thirdly, The wrongs done to Religion ſpoke in the ſame dealect, and was a part of that fewel, for <hi>Bethel</hi> was become <hi>Bethaven:</hi> the <hi>Trojan</hi> horſe of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49068:19"/>having entered the Ghurch of <hi>England,</hi> with an <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in the Belly thereof: and that at length it might be brought to this Land, like the Altar of <hi>Damaſcus:</hi> Was there not exotick formes of Government moulded above, to make a gap for that Belgick Monſter here? ſo that Religion mourning, cryed out with the Church, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The wayes of Zion do mourn, becauſe none come to the ſolemn feaſts: all her gates are deſolate: her prieſts ſigh, her vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins are afflicted, and ſhe is in bitterneſſe.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Tribunal Seats of Juſtice cryed againſt them; Novices, and Children as to ſuch imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being left to Adminiſter Juſtice; Dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Sword-men were turned into Judges, a ſtrange kind of Metamorphoſis! They did ſuppoſe that their Sword had a kind of Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, like the fiery tounges to the Apoſtles, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediat qualification. I never heard of, nor ſaw any of our Learned Lawyers (who for the wel of the people were neceſſitate to plead) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, but it put me in minde of ſome Pilgrims, ſaying over their Matins, to the Lady of <hi>Loretto;</hi> for they underſtood no more what was ſpoke unto them, nor that ſtatue there, what is uttered by the Pilgrims: So our Laws were wreſted, not only through affection to their followers, but alſo through Ignorance how to execute the ſame. Fifthly, Many impoveriſhed and born down family by unjuſt Forfeiture, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49068:19"/>Sequeſtration, and their inhancing all Traffick to themſelves, cryed to God, <hi>That for the oppreſſion of the poor, and the fighs of the priſoners, he would ariſe</hi> Laſtly, The blond of many of all Degrees, ſhed not only in War, but in Peace and in cold blood, cruelly as well as unjuſtly:<note place="margin">Tutl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</note> the burying of ſeveral perſons before their breath expired, and ſelling others as Slaves, all theſe called <hi>for vengeance and for fire to come out from Shechem againſt Abimelech, and from Abimelech to deſtroy She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem.</hi> Theſe were the fewel amongſt them of Gods indignation, the friends appearing for us to ſpeak a word for the oppreſſed, were Gods Mercy, His Faithfulneſſe, and His Juſtice; His Mercy pleaded for pity, His Faithfulneſſe for accompliſhment of His promiſe, His Juſtice for vindication of His people; His Mercy ſtirred Him up to help, His Faithfulneſſe to make haſte, His Juſtice to avenge: ſo that you ſee clearly here, the repreſentation of that <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> and deſerved ruine of theſe bloudy Traitors, both as to its manner and motives.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. How may honeſt-hearted upright men, ſit down and bleſſe God that they have been keeped in bad times, from medling with theſe Monſters! ſuch have yet keeped (though, it may be, they have looſed much) a very preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous jewel, that theſe who have gained moſt in theſe times, never took pains to poſſeſſe, a good
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49068:20"/>conſcience, which is better nor all the others rich attainments: and beſides that, much honour, and now they may hope to reap the fruits of their integrity and faithfulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. We may hereby ſee that it is not ſo eaſie as every one doth imagine, to read the Book of Providence: Though Uſurpers may have a fair Gaile of ſucceſſe, filling all their Sails for a while; yet the fire of Gods wrath may ſeaze on their Ship at laſt, and ſtop the courſe of their Domination, it is then evil argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Providence. God in the depth of His Wiſdom by His Providence in this late change, hath defeat all arguments therefrom, by which they endeavoured to prove the equity of their unparalleled rebellion and cruelty.</p>
                  <p>Thus we have ſpoke to the removal of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful <hi>external power:</hi> We come now to ſpeak of the removing of the <hi>internal and infernal power of ſin,</hi> which followeth as naturally one the other, as the ſhaddow doth on the body; for in point of policie, Uſurpers connive at ſin for keeping up of themſelves, though that power leaneth on a weak reed that hath ſuch ſupporters. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this we ſhall ſpeka to two things; Firſt, Of the thing purged out: Secondly, Of the manner of its out-purging. Firſt, Of the thing purged out, it is <hi>droſſe and tinne,</hi> where you may behold the nature of all ſin in the general. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Of one ſin in particular.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49068:20"/>
                  <p>Firſt, Of all ſin in the general, it is unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, this is ſet out by the title given to it, <hi>(droſſe)</hi> which is ſimply unprofitable, and <hi>(tinn)</hi> which is unprofitable comparatively in regard of Silver or Gold. Hence take this <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Sin, it is an upofitable thing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thiſtles?</hi> no more can the grapes of any ſpiritual comfort, or the figs of true contentment be gathered off the thiſtles and thornes of ſin; and if we will either look to its contrary or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, we will perceive it a truth unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
                  <p>It's contrary: the thing, that is directly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſin, is Godlineſſe: theſe two are als far oppoſit to one another, as good is to evil, and Godlineſs of its nature being gainful, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6. ſin muſt not be any wayes advantagious: I know there be ſome like <hi>Gehazi</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaineth an Atheiſtical conceat, that a holy walking with God ſpoileth profit: Concerning whom, I find a Reverend Divine ſay, ſuch hath ſtroak hands with the devil, upon the tearms which our Saviour refuſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.6. But, I ſay, upon leſſe nor the hundred part of theſe tearms, yea the truth is, ſinful walking, utterly ſpoileth honeſt and lawful profit.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Behold the conſequences, Firſt, Shame, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.19. If the condition of a perſon be ſuch, as he cannot profit his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49068:21"/>factor in any thing, yet he ought to be ſure that he perturb him in nothing; he that doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, cannot but be aſhamed to look him on the face. God he is thus to us, but we perturbing him in every thing, cannot but he aſhamed in end: Thus <hi>Adam</hi> made a poor game of it, in eating of the forbidden fruit, he found himſelf naked, and was aſhamed to look his Lord and Benefactor on the face; If that ſin be profitable, that produceth no better fruits, judge ye.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond conſequence is Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. What a death? Eternal death; he that hath wrought all the week in drudgery, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth at the end of the week his wages, payed in the black coyn of death, hath made but a very ſory bargain; but he that hath lived all his life in ſin, hath his wages payed In a blacker coyn nor bodily, even in eternal death: ſo that they are worſe than mad that are not convinced of the unprofitablneſſe of ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. We may ſee hence that the world is in a great miſtake: If ye tell the drunkard, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean perſon, the covetous man this truth, they will not receive it, nor evidence ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as to give it entertainment but for one day; the reaſon is, he looketh through carnal perſpectives, which preſenteth all ſin green and pleaſant, and richly loaden with the fruits of advantage; which miſtake is cured by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, looking to ſin with a ſpiritual eye, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49068:21"/>weighing and pondering the ſame in the ballance of the Sanctuary: this whoſoever doth, ſhall be taught the thoughts and language of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 6.21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is ſin ſo unprofitable then? (Sirs) this affordeth me an earand to your ſouls, and it is this: to exhort, intreat, beg and obteſt you by the mercies of God, and the loves of Chriſt, to forſake ſin: Are you children, to be chaſing ſhaddows? fools, to believe all to be gold that gliſters? Or, are you men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>ad majora nati,</hi> born to greater things, than with <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> to be catching Flees? As you would not have theſe joyful dayes, this golden age of much contentment to loure upon us, and prove as one ſaid of the Summer of this ſame Country, that it was hot, but ſhort: let us all beware of this unprofitable thing, ſin: Have theſe in former generations who have made the greateſt purchaſe of this ſtuff, been the moſt happy and proſperous men in their Eſtates? Or hath not God drawn them out as in a map into his moſt wiſe Providence, <hi>in exempla aliorum,</hi> to be Beakens unto others? making them to lye down with their bones full of the ſins of their youth, their conſciences turning unto a hell of terrours, and all the mountains of Riches and preferments acquired by them, melting away as the untimely birth, or the Snow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun: Then I beſeech you, be no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49068:22"/>worſe than <hi>Johns</hi> Auditors, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. who were <hi>forwarned to flie from the wrath to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having ſpoken to the nature of all ſin in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral: now we come to ſpeak of the nature of one in particular, which is hypocrifie, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented here metaphorically by tinne, and it cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterizeth this ſin very exactly: For tinne, it hath (when it is well refined) a very ſhyning quality, which giveth ſome reſemblance of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and hypocrifie it hath the ſame property, a gliſtering ſhew, and thereby doth not a little reſemble holineſſe: Hence this <hi>Doctrine</hi> may be gathered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Hypocriſie is a deceiving ſin, it ſhineth as it were holineſſe; but it is as far from it, as the one Pole is from the other, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſin under the mantle of Piety: and therefore Chriſt calleth Hypocrites, painted walls, whited tombs, it is a dung-hill of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety under the luſter of piety: So the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſhot very near the mark that did call it a <hi>ſubtile evil, a ſecret poyſon, a lurking venome, the paint of virtue, and the moth of ſanctity.</hi> For there nothing giveth holineſſe a greater blow, than unholineſſe under the pretence of holineſſe: this is, to have the <hi>form of Godlineſſe, without the power thereof.</hi> The devil in other ſins, is but in his country apparel, here he is in his neateſt and court dreſſe, he dreſſeth up other ſins in a Wooden, but this in a Silver diſh. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49068:22"/>this ſin, theſe two are to be enquired after. 1. Where it is learned? 2. Who are the Schollers?</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Where it is learned? even at the devils univerſity, the great maſter, being an old practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer thereof from the beginning, having ſuch nimbleneſſe in acting it, <hi>as he can transform himſelf into an angel of light:</hi> this is one of the devils black Artes that he teacheth here, and as his image and ſuperſcription is thereupon, ſo it ſealeth upon the Students thereof, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame, and at their reckoning with the great Judge, theſe that are under this ſtamp, will be rendered up to its owner.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, Who are the great Students in this School, and the beſt proficients? Indeed it is very throng, and many are taking pains to make progreſſe; but theſe who carry away the Lawrel of greateſt proficiency, are the <hi>Pſeudo</hi>-Chriſtian, and the <hi>Pſeudo</hi>-Politician, the falſe Chriſtian, and the falſe States-man.</p>
                  <p>The falſe Chriſtian, to cover his other ſins, in doing which, he diſcovers them more to God, making them to appear in a crimſon colour: The covetous man, to cover his covetouſneſſe, he maketh uſe of it as a cloak, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.5. The unclean perſons, to cover their uncleanneſſe as the <hi>Antinomians</hi> and <hi>Libertines, turning the Grace of God into wantonneſſe:</hi> The treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous man to cover his treachery; ſo <hi>Judas</hi> took
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49068:23"/>the Sacrament of the Paſſeover, before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his Maſter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The falſe Politician (for the true Statesman hateth it as the cheat of a Rogue) he profiteth much in this Arte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd uſeth it as a cloak to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his rebellion, imitating <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who when he intended to uſurp the Crown of his Father, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to go to <hi>Hebron</hi> to perform a vow, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.7. And <hi>Jehu,</hi> who deſigning to ſnatch the Scepter of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> puts on and boaſteth of broad phylacteries of zeal for God; and if the people he purpoſeth to inſtrument, be fanatick, he can pray with them, and if need be, preach alſo, <hi>Nam nemo cautius malus eſt, quam qui ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconditur ſub appellatione pietatis.</hi> 2. To cover their bloody oppreſſion, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Jezabel</hi> and <hi>Achab</hi> calleth a faſt, that under the colour thereof, they may out <hi>Naboth</hi> of his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; and if one faſt be not ſufficient, his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not being to oppreſſe one perſon, or fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but a nation, or many nations, the faſt muſt be frequent, yea, monethly, that people may be amuzed, as well as God is evidently abuſed by their ſophiſtical devotion. 3. To cover his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution with ſome pretence of honeſty or holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo <hi>Herod</hi> muſt take <hi>Johns</hi> life becauſe of his oath, an oath being an act of Religion, he wrappeth up this his cruelty in the ſpecious pretention of piety.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Is hypocriſie ſo deceiving a ſin? The
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49068:23"/>counterfeit of Vertue? The Ape of Religion? Then hypocrits, they muſt be counterfeit Saints, the Apes of Holy-men; yet they do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them ſo much, but a diſcerning eye may rid the marches betwixt them, by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing marks. Firſt, The hypocrite muſtereth out all his good deeds to vain oſtentation, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.1. like the Ape, ever carrying her young in her armes, to make the world believe, he is near to the border of perfection, when indeed, his life is a Folio Book of Errataes or Errours; but the Godly man walketh humbly and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all his dayes: thinking with <hi>Paul,</hi> he is to be reckoned among <hi>the leaſt of Saints.</hi> Secondly, The hypocrite is alwayes prying into the faults and eſcapes of his neighbour, and (as <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> lifted up the Plough over the childe thrown in before him) they make their obſervation paſſe their own follies and failings, <hi>Matths.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11. but the Godly mans diſcoveries, are moſt at home: he knoweth there is within himſelf a <hi>terra incognita,</hi> an unknown land, and thither he taketh frequent voyages, that he may not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be unacquainted with himſelf. Thirdly, His conſcience is very touchy and tender as to the mint and aniſe of ſome civil queſtions, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the word of God doth moſt clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine them; but as to harder mettalled mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, his conſcience is nothing inferiour to the ſtomack of the Oſtrich, he can ſwallow rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49068:24"/>without any ſcruple, ſo being this piece of iron be guilded: whereas the Godly and orderly Chriſtian, ſtarts not debates in civil concernments; nor can he endure but his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhould be in an exact parallel to the Scriptures, and ſo claſſeth rebellion with the ſin of witchcraft. Fourthly, The hypocrite, though he pretends he valueth not the world, but that Chriſt is all in all to him, yet he is ſo great an Idolizer thereof, that he ſeemeth to be of the opinion of old <hi>Hermes,</hi> that the viſible world is the Image of the inviſible: and it is upon this account he payeth his adoration thereto; but the Godly man is like the Church in the <hi>Revel.</hi> with the Moon (the Embleme of the world) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet, trading on it as the moſt uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of vanities. Laſtly, Hypocrites are cruel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.16. both in their judgment and in their practice: as they condemn all that are not of their judgement; ſo if it lay in their power, with one ſtroak they would cut off the heads of them all: and yet though they be <hi>Nero's,</hi> they muſt be called <hi>Cato's: Falſis veri imaginibus cuncta evertere moliuntur:</hi> but the Godly is merciful and lendeth, meaſuring his affairs with juſtice, and is far from their blaſphemy, to think Chriſt was in a miſtake when he prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited us to judge according to the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Bleſſe God who in his juſt Providence
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49068:24"/>is apulling off the vizard of hypocriſie from mens faces, and all theſe diſguiſes of Religion, <hi>In which the rough horns of their private deſigns was wrapped up.</hi> Men of late were only valued to be of worth and parts, according to their diſſimulation or hypocriſie: had a man any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to the Uſurpers, and therewith a ſhow of Godlineſſe, according to his profeſſion, Civil, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred or Military? he was fit for any Truſt; theſe two would have qualified him ſufficiently: Learning, Judgement, Ingenuity, Loyal-courage, were eſteemed ſcandalous: If any flaſh of wit had eſcaped a man, he had been in hazard of looſing his reputation: Have we not reaſon then to bleſſe God for freeing us from ſuch a miſerable thraldom.</p>
                  <p>Having ſpoke to the thing purged out (ſin and hypocriſie) We ſhall next enter upon the manner how it is done. Firſt, In regard of God, and theſe two things will fall to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By what he doth it? Next, In what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he doth it? By what? It is by fire; for as I have ſaid, the word <hi>Tſaraph</hi> is a word proper to Gold-ſmiths, ſignifying melting, and this cannot be without fire, and ſo the Nown is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Verb. Now fire here as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth to ſin and hypocriſie, can be no other but the energie and efficacious working of Gods own Spirit, <hi>He will baptize you with the holy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49068:25"/>Ghoſt and with fire,</hi> Matth. 3.11. His Spirit is called <hi>the ſpirit of burning,</hi> Iſa. 4.4. The Spirit of God working in us, hath a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance with the operation of fire, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it diſcovereth the various and manifold ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of His Spirit in our Renovation, which is the Chriſtians ſpiritual refining from his droſſe and tinne. Secondly, In what extent doth he it? He doth it in a full extent, <hi>All thy tinne.</hi> Which <hi>(All)</hi> ſuppoſeth another <hi>(All)</hi> for if all our tinne be to be purged, then all our droſſe alſo, Gods Spirit will not be pleaſed though all our hypocriſie be removed, if groſſe and palpable ſins be permitted to remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified, and this is done in the progreſſe of our Sanctification.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The manner in regard of man, is couched in the word, <hi>purge</hi> or <hi>melt,</hi> and that hint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h at its difficulty as to him, that it is not eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but as hard as to have droſſe ſeparate by fire from the mettal: And here I preſent you theſe three <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, There is an univerſal removing of ſin in our Renovation and Sanctification. Secondly, There be various and manifold effects ſhown by Gods Spirit in his removal of ſin. Thirdly, This removing of ſin in our Renovation and Sanctification, is not an eaſie, but a difficult work. 1. There is an univerſal removing of ſin in our Sanctification and Renovation, not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49068:25"/>only of the groſſer ſins, but of our moſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſins; not only of ſins in our life, but ſins in our heart; not only of prophanity, but hypocriſie; and not only one branch, but every branch, both of profanity and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, are removed. Firſt, As to there blot and ſtain, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, As to our delight unto them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. Thirdly, As to their dominion over us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> laſt, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. Yet this removal is not ſo univerſal as to remove ſin, according to its being: that remaineth and will, ſo long as we are upon earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us follow this way for our perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reformation, labouring to be renued in the ſpirit of the mind, <hi>and to become ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as our Lord is holy, in all manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation;</hi> for there is no peſonal Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion acceptable, without perſonal Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this is only true and ſincere: And it is ſuch a Reformation that theſe happy times calleth for at our hands. Is God reforming all outwardly that hath been out of order in theſe Kingdoms? Let us Anſwer this by ſetting a work Spiritual Reformation in our ſelves: who offereth a falſe perſonal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to God, underſtandeth not the nature of that benefit God actually beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on us. Theſe many years by gone, we
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49068:26"/>have had a falſe Head of the body politick, Bloody Uſurpers: There hath been a falſe Repreſentative of theſe Kingdoms, contrary to Law and Reaſon: a <hi>Juncto</hi> of all the three Kingdoms gathered together: There hath been a falſe Bench of Juſtice, as to the Conſtitution thereof: And in ſome ſenſe, there hath been a falſe diſpenſation of Goſpel Ordinances, by Souldiers and other Laymen, who were not called, as was <hi>Aaron,</hi> and of ſuch Stuff as had not God for its Author: There was alſo a falſe Reformation of peoples lives by a pretended Holineſſe, theſe were all like the Time, a degenerate Time, and degenerate Cuſtomes. Now we have got the true Head of the Body politick, our Dear and Dread Soveraign the Kings Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: hopes of a true Repreſentative, a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament according to the Laws of the Land: and of a true and upright Bench of Juſtice: the true way of diſpenſing Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, liberate from Uſurpation. Let then our Perſonal Reformation be true alſo, by being truely Reformed, which can be no other wayes, than by being renewed in the ſpirit of the mind, and walking in new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and holineſſe before God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. Manifold are the effects of Gods Spirit in our Renovation: fire hath not more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49068:26"/>ſeveral effects, than hath the Spirit of God in this work: <hi>Bernard</hi> reduceth them to three: ſaith he, <hi>Datur Spiritus ut doceat, moveat, moneat,</hi> The Spirit is given to teach, to move our hearts, and to admoniſh: By which three the Chriſtians ſoul is made to ſhare of three notable benefits. Firſt, He receiveth thereby <hi>ſplendorem,</hi> that is, the light of Divine Knowledge; for as fire bringeth outward light, ſo this bringeth inward. Secondly, <hi>Fervorem</hi> the quiken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his dead affections to a holy zeal for God; for as fire is accompanied with heat, ſo is the Spirit of God in its operation. Thirdly, <hi>Timorem,</hi> Many times fire produce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this affect of fear, through peoples inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertancy: But that holy fear the Chriſtian partaketh of, is a genuine proper effect of the work of Gods Spirit, by which he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in awe to ſin againſt God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. If we ſhould follow out the effects hereof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its ſimilitude unto fire, we would find many more beſides theſe, as <hi>Preparation;</hi> for as fire prepareth meat for our bodies, ſo the Spirit prepareth the Word to the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of our ſouls. Secondly, <hi>Purging</hi> as fire of mettal, ſo this purgeth out the droſs of ſin. Thirdly, <hi>Aſſimulation,</hi> turning to its own nature man, as fire to the nature
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49068:27"/>thereof things conbuſtible. Fourthly, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> beingias refreſhing to our ſouls in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, as fire is to our bodies, when the ſeaſon through cold is moſt unpleaſant; but we ſhall not inſiſt in perſuing this point any further, but break off therefrom in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us ſeek the Spirit of Grace to dwell unto us, that we may ſhare of theſe happy effects; for as there is no beginning of Renovation without him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. nor progreſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. neither conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. ſo there is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable gratulation and rejoycing in God. If we do go about this duty, and in a right manner, it muſt be in his ſtrength: this is the fire that muſt kindle the ſacrifice of our praiſes, as <hi>Veſta's</hi> ſire when it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, behoved to be kindled from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the aſſiſtance and help of a Beam from the Sun; ſo muſt the fire of our gratulatory devotion this day, by a beam from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Sanctification, be blown up unto a holy and religious flame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. This removing of ſin in our Sanctification and Renovation, is not an eaſie, but a very difficult work: therefore Chriſt calleth it <hi>a plucking out of the eyes, and cutting off the hand.</hi> Theſe following
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49068:27"/>Conſiderations will make the Doctrine evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, There is againſt it Armies of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: nature in its ſtrength doth ſtand in the way thereof, muſtering up mans inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. mans will, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40. his affections, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. the devil is againſt it, who is a roaring lyon ſeeking whom he may devoure, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. the world alſo marching out with flying colours againſt the ſame: <hi>In the luſt of the eye, the luſt of the fleſh, and the pride of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, It cannot but be difficult in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the exact conformity required to the Patern, which is the Image of God: no garb of Holineſſe being approven in the Court of Heaven, but looked upon as an Antick dreſſe, and quite out of faſhion, that anſwereth not to this, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.23, 24.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The greatneſſe and large extent of this work, aſſerteth the difficulty not to be ſmall; for it is no leſſe than the turning upſide down of a whole world, even the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> and little world of man: And if the greater World, as to the turning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down of the Worſhip thereinto, created ſuch pains to the Apoſtles: no queſtion, this change in the trampling under foot our luſts and vile affections, which hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49068:28"/>over our heads, cannot but be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſome ſhare of trouble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Though it be difficult this work of Renovation and Sanctification, yet we muſt not deſpond, and through overwhelming thoughts of diſcouragement give it over, but more ſeriouſly ſet our ſelves to work thereinto, <hi>What is difficult to man, is eaſie to God:</hi> humane difficulties, yea impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, are conquerable by Omnipotency, we will not give over a worldly buſineſſe for difficulties, and ſhall we be ſo baſe, as to lay aſide an heavenly upon this ſcore: It is a heavenly violence that taketh heaven, a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent and painful combate with our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a violent and conſtant wreſtling by prayer in the Mediator Chriſt, with our Creator. The neceſſity. of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. The honour of it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. The effects of it: Firſt ſelf-denial, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.23. Secondly, Shunning of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13. The happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thereof, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. are all encouragements very great and ſingular, which joyntly pondered, will weigh down the diſcouragement of the works difficulty: There is great neceſſity for the earneſt urging of this; for what will outward proſperity, outward joy and rejoycing, the Reſurrection of your civil Intereſts avail, without this:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49068:28"/>Will your immunities, and priviledges, or freedom, afford you contentment, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to your expectation, if you be not Gods freemen? If your ſouls be yet in bonds, what will the ſtopping of the carrear of uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing domination, and the daſhing of theſe hell-hatched deſigns do? If the Uſurper ſin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe domination, and command in your ſouls, giving the deſigns of Satan ſtill a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Let this be pondered by you in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, leaſt your laughter and joy tend to, and end in bitter mourning, let the yoke of the internal uſurper with that of the external be broke in pieces. The Lord give us ſtrength ſo to do, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:29"/>
                  <p>SCOTIA REDIVIVA, OR <hi>SCOTLANDS</hi> Reſurrection. SERMON II.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Pſal. 30.11.</bibl> Thou haſt turned my mourning unto joy, thou haſt looſed my ſack, and girded me with gladneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Verſ. 12.</bibl> Therefore ſhall my tongue praiſe thee and not ceaſe: O Lord my God, I will give thanks unto thee for ever.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 18.47.</bibl>
                     <p>It is God that avengeth me, and ſubdueth the people under me.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 54.7.</bibl>
                     <p>For he hath delivered me out of all trouble, and my eye hath ſeen his deſire upon my enemies.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tu velut eximium poſt triſtia nubila tandem</l>
                        <l>Sidus ades; Tu bella fugas, pacemque reducis,</l>
                        <l>Tu leges &amp; jura novas. Te praeſide, rerum</l>
                        <l>Grata redit facies, Certuſque renaſcitur ordo, &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Utere jure tuo quicquid rectumve piumve</l>
                        <l>Eſſe putas ſervare jube: nos vero, volentes</l>
                        <l>Omnia ſuſcipimus: libertas maxima nobis</l>
                        <l>Tam placido parere viro.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Guntherus,</hi> lib. 8. v. 535.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Alta cernens non deficio,</l>
                     <l>Virtus onerata triumphat.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by a Society of <hi>Stationers, Anno Dom.</hi> 1661.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:30"/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:49068:30"/>
                  <head>SCOTIA REDIVIVA, OR <hi>Scotlands</hi> Reſurrection. SERMON II.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Iſa. 1.26.</bibl>
                        <p>I will reſtere thy Judges as at firſt, and thy Counſellours as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E</hi> have ſpoke of the <hi>malum ablatum,</hi> We come now to the <hi>bonum collatum: I will reſtore thy Judges as at firſt,</hi> &amp;c. As in the Verſe preceeding, you have the extirpation of Uſurpers; ſo here ye have the Reſtauration of the Lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate faithfully promiſed: In which promiſe you have ſomewhat imported, and ſomewhat reported.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49068:31"/>
                  <p>Firſt, Somewhat imported, and that is, the decay of Lawful Magiſtracy in <hi>Judah,</hi> the wonted Glory and Honour due thereto, being under cloud: the time of which darkneſſe being then, when <hi>Senacherib</hi> came up againſt <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> taking all the fenced Cities of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah:</hi> Or elſe in the time of <hi>Achaz</hi> when the Kingdom was under the feet of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> and under the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. who did poſſeſſe and rule over the Cities of the low Countries, giving Law to them at their pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> The Lawful and Supream Magiſtrate may have his due Glory and Greatneſſe for a time eclipſed, ſo was it with <hi>Achaz,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> ruling in many places of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: Yea, what is more ſtrange, ſo was it with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> a good and a gracious King, <hi>Senacherib</hi> overrunneth all, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36. But what is ſtrangeſt, <hi>David</hi> was not only a gracious Prince to his people, but a man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods own heart, and yet his greatneſſe is brought under cloud in a ſudden, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon why the Lord permitteth this, is, That he may puniſh people for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Lawful Authority: <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not ſenſible of their felicity and proſperous dayes under their Religious and Gracious King,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49068:31"/>
                     <hi>David,</hi> but wearying of his reign, and itching after a new Governour, therefore he ſuffers <hi>Abſolom</hi> to uſurp the Throne, that he might puniſh their ingratitude to God for ſo good a King, and the diſloyalty of their hearts to ſo gracious a Maſter.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond reaſon is, For puniſhing of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates for the abuſe of their power; for though God hath exempted Kings as his Vicegerents from the puniſhment of men, yet he keepeth this prerogative for himſelf: And therefore though God promiſed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Kingdom to <hi>Davids</hi> poſterity, yet he reſerved the Authority of chaſtiſing of them for their ſins.</p>
                  <p>A third reaſon is, That he may fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Kings for the great matters he hath to imploy them into, doing like a wiſe Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, who digs loweſt when and where he mindeth to build higheſt, humbling theſe moſt whom he intendeth to exalt to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt pitch of eminency: <hi>David</hi> muſt not come to the Crown God had given him right to, at firſt, but muſt reign ſome years at <hi>Hebron,</hi> before he get the Throne and Crown of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 Sam. 5.5.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That people may be the more convinced of their advantage they have by a Lawful Authority, and their proſperous
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49068:32"/>condition under the ſame, after they have taſted of the bloody and bitter effects of Uſurpation, and may behold the Lords ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative goodneſſe to them, in reſtoring of the ſame again.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, That he may inſtruct Princes, of whom it is they hold their Crowns, and upon whoſe Good-will their Soveraignity doth depend: The Lord doth by this as in a Table, draw before their eyes and face in great Capital Letters, that it is by him <hi>that Kings raign, and Princes decree juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Behold here what will be the caſe of Loyal Subjects: May their Maſter be brought down from his Greatneſſe and Glory, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fare well with them the members of the Body, muſt ſympathize with the Head: their condition we have pinſelled out in that of <hi>Davids</hi> Loyal Subjects and faithful Servsnts, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. Their enjoyments will be imbittered to them, and their ſpirits under a cloud of diſcontent, living in the world as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>Achimaz,</hi> when they were hid in the well of <hi>Bethuram,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.20, 21. in a ſhade of obſcurity, with ſuch a darkneſſe of ſorrow upon their ſpirits, as that which was upon the face of the deep, in the firſt day of the Creation: This hath been the carriage and condition of many thouſands in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49068:32"/>this Land, but the fury of the enemy hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them from their retirement, chaſing them from mountain to mountain, and from corner to corner:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. What then will the carriage of Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors be, when as their condition through the eclipſe of the Lawful Magiſtrate will be proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, his fall being the riſe of ſuch, and the harveſt in which they reap the reward of their baſeneſſe? Queſtionleſſe, ſuch will be blown up in a timpynie of pride, and will ſpeak pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous things, and like <hi>Owles</hi> in the night, come abroad boldly looking big upon all. We have ſeen ſuch a generation as theſe, and ſuch a carriage as this with our eyes; and there was a fourfold <hi>Owl</hi> or <hi>Noctambulo,</hi> who theſe years bypaſt came abroad, and walked in pride. Firſt, The Souldier <hi>Noctambulo</hi> or night <hi>Owle,</hi> who was the Gentleman Uſher to the reſt; he under pretence of Liberty, brought all men in thraldome; and for the defence of an upſtart Commonwealth, brought all the Country unto utter poverty, theſe as the froges with which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was ſmitten, ſwarmed both in City and Country, in our Fields and in our Houſes. The ſecond <hi>Owle</hi> or <hi>Noctambulo,</hi> was the Schiſmatick, who under the pretence of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both intitling and intailing to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49068:33"/>the name of true Chriſtians, made a gape both in the Civil, to let in and keep up the Uſurper: And alſo in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Government, to throw it down, and to make way for Liberty of Conſcience. The third <hi>Owle</hi> that cometh abroad in this night time, was the Sectarian, a <hi>Nactambulo,</hi> who under high pretentions of Religion, invadeth the Doctrine, as the other had done the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church: And that he might do it with the greater ſucceſſe, he muſt cry up their <hi>Diana</hi> of Uſurpation, and defame the Lords Deputy and Vicegerent. The laſt <hi>Owle</hi> or <hi>Nactambulo,</hi> was the <hi>Mammoniſt,</hi> who to keep his riches, did loſſe his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, coming abroad to Court the Foxe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of neceſſity, fathering the ſame upon providence, as if this had called him to fall down to worſhip the Beaſt, that he might ſave his Eſtate and Means, <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis nemo à Deo anguſtiatur ad peccandum.</hi> Theſe were the Birds that waited on the Bird of prey in the night time of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
                  <p>Having ſpoke to that which is imported, We come next to what is reported: And it is the bringing the Lawful and Ancient Magiſtracy, the Royal Power of <hi>Judah</hi> to the wonted pitch of Luſter, Glory and
<pb facs="tcp:49068:33"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:49068:34"/>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49068:34"/>Extent: <hi>I will reſtore your Judges as at the firſt.</hi> Here be three things worthy of our ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after: Firſt, A favour. Secondly, The mould in which the favour is caſt. Thirdly, The Moulder or great Artiſt that ſhapes this favour after that faſhion. Firſt, The favour, and it is twofold, a principal one or maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, <hi>I will reſtore your Judges as at the firſt, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond is ſubordinate and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſeful, though it be not of that degree with the firſt, <hi>And your Counſellours as at the beginning:</hi> Which you may take aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in theſe three, A twofold object, and one act: We ſhall begin with the object, The firſt of which is <hi>(thy Judges)</hi> The word in the firſt Language is <hi>Shephtaich,</hi> which is often uſed for the Inferiour, yet fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently alſo (as is evident from the Book of <hi>Judges</hi>) for the Supream Magiſtrate: I find moſt of the Interpreters take it in this ſenſe here: And becauſe judging is one of the moſt eminent acts of Magiſtracy, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate borroweth his denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefrom: And indeed, it is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement for Kings to be ſtilled ſo, when God who is the King of Kings taketh this Epithite, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.7. But here it may be objected, that it cannot be well applyed to the Magiſtrate of <hi>Judah</hi> who was a ſingle
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49068:35"/>perſon, becauſe the word is in the Plural Number. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Prophet is not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one King perſonally, but to a Series of them, a Succeſſion of Kings, and this maketh him ſpeak of them in the Plural Number: I will give you a Line of Kings ſuch as ye had before, with the Glory and Extent due to them, yet this was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed abſolutely, but conditionally if they walked like his people, which they not doing, his promiſe was not binding.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond object is <hi>Counſellours:</hi> Which I find ſome underſtand of the Inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: Indeed, the Reſtauration of the Superiour, uſeth to raiſe up the Inferiour Magiſtrate, and the latter is a conſequent of the former, theſe two are chained to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Others by Counſellours underſtand theſe (to which I incline) who are aſſiſting to the Supream Authority by their counſels, of which we read, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 27.32. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.16.</p>
                  <p>For the act, it is reſtoring, it is <hi>Shub</hi> in the Original, and it ſignifieth to return, make reſt, quiet and reſtore; and it look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to both theſe objects, as wel Judges as Counſellours, to the firſt principally, and to the other ſeondarly.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49068:35"/>
                  <p>The ſecond thing in the words, is, The mould according to which the favour is caſt: And it is twofold as the favour it ſelf is. And the firſt is, <hi>(as at the firſt)</hi> Some I find to expound this, as to the firſt way of their Magiſtrates, which was by <hi>Judges;</hi> but that Government was neither ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, profitable nor honourable, as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Kings, and ſo would not be the right Baſe to build their comfort up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The latter Interpreters leaveth thoſe of this Judgement: I think one of theſe two muſt be the intent of Gods Spirit: <hi>As at the firſt,</hi> to look to <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> I will raiſe you up Kings ſuch as they were, Godly and Wiſe Kings, ſuch as theſe were of old: Or elſe, <hi>as at the firſt,</hi> may refer to the Regal Authority; I will give you Kings with ſuch an extent of their Royal Power, as they were wont to have before Invaſion, not only exerciſed in ſome few Cities in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> but ſtreached out over all <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Dominions belonging thereto.</p>
                  <p>For the mould of the Counſellours, <hi>as at the beginning,</hi> I think it may refer either to the firſt foundation of that Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that Line of the Family of <hi>David,</hi> who indeed were Wiſe, Prudent and Vigilant
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49068:36"/>Men: Or to ſome Wiſe Counſellours, who had been with theſe Kings at their entry to their Raign, and were removed by death, through want of whoſe counſel their Affairs had not been ſo proſperous as of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>The laſt particular, is, The moulder of both theſe, the Author of this double Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, both of the matter and manner of it, which is God, a work fit for ſuch a Hand, and a Hand fit for ſuch a work: Hence I ſhall preſent you with theſe following <hi>Doctrines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, That it is a great mercy for a people to have their righteous King reſtored, after long eclipſe of his Greatneſſe. Secondly, This Mercy is heightened when a people receiveth ſuch a King, ſurrounded with prudent and pious Counſellours.Thirdly, That it is God alone who raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and reſtoreth fallen and lapſed Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. Fourthly, It is the ſame God who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth to their wonted Honours and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Noble, Wiſe and Faithful Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
                  <p>As to the firſt, That it is a great Mercy to have a Righteous King reſtored, after the long Eclipſe of his Greatneſſe: The Lord
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49068:36"/>would not have promiſed this to <hi>Judah</hi> at ſo remarkable a time, as this in <hi>Hezekiah</hi> or <hi>Achaz</hi> his thraldome, if it had not been of ſingular eminency. <hi>Davids</hi> Reſtauration after <hi>Abſolon</hi> his unnatural conſpiracy, and the change of <hi>Athaliah</hi> her Uſurpation unto <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh</hi> his happy inauguration, maketh the point evident: But beſides all this, what the Word of God attributeth to Kings, doth plainly imply this truth; for in Scripture they are intitled, the <hi>Light of Iſrael, the Breath of our Noſtrils, and the ſhaddow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we reſt:</hi> To have our eyes reſtored after depravation of them, our breath after we have been almoſt ſtiffled, or a refreſhing ſhade in the ſcorching heat of Summer, or in the time of a tempeſtuous rain, are without all peradventure, very refreſhing and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to theſe houſes of duſt: even ſo is the reſtitution of a Righteous Prince unto a people, chained unto a heavy bondage, and juſtly compared with light to the eyes, breath to the noſtrils, and a ſhelter againſt all their perſecuters.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon hereof, is, Becauſe ſuch (Juſt and Righteous Kings) are the only fitteſt for the Government of Kingdoms: And that in a fourfold reſpect.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49068:37"/>
                  <p>Firſt, In regard of extraction, people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon that conſideration more ready to yeeld unto them chearful obedience, whereas otherwiſe they are very like to vex and grudge at others, who preſum to ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to lord it over theſe to whom they are ſcarce equals; But the Son, Righteous Heir and immediate Succeſſor of a King, is cordially imbraced with chearfulneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of all the people, unleſſe it be by ſome few Traitors, who are the bane of people, and the reproach of Kingdoms.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, In regard of Parts, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from a Princely Stem, Parents ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, and inured unto ſuch imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as attends Magiſtracy: <hi>Nec imbellem feroces progenerant aquilae columbam,</hi> The valiant and couragious Eagle doth not beget a ſilly and ſimple Dove. Beſides that, from their very Cradle they are bred to what is moſt ſuitable to ſuch high and eminent Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, In regard of their indubitable Intereſt and Right as from God, ſo likewiſe from man. Hence it is, that ſuch for the moſt part, ſet before them the advantage of the people, rather than that of their own, reſembling in this, the prudence of wiſe and tender-hearted Parents, for as much
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49068:37"/>as they uſually moderate and temper their Government, according to the condition and exigence of the Governed.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Becauſe of the Execution of the Law; for by ſuch, the Laws will be fully, duely and faithfully execute: according to that of Cicero, <hi>Vere dici poteſt Magiſtratum eſſe legem loquentem, legem autem eſſe mutum Magiſtratum:</hi> That is, the Magiſtrate may be truely ſaid to be the Law ſpeaking, and the Law to be the Magiſtrate ſilent; But when an Uſurper gets into the Throne, he is not the Law ſpeaking, but in this caſe the Law is Tougne-tyed; for if the Laws were ſuffered to ſpeak, they would command him to the door.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. What a great Mercy hath this Land got, in the reſtoring of our King to the Thrones of his Anceſtors, to all the Glory and Rights of his Fathers, and the due extent of his Greatneſſe. The word in the Original, <hi>Shub,</hi> here tranſlated Reſtore, hath five ſignifications, each whereof repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the matter under a diſtinct notion, and will help us to look upon this favour in its due latitude. Firſt, It ſignifieth to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.25. And indeed in this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, we may behold Mercy that we ſee him again with our eyes, after ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49068:38"/>at Home, ſo many hazards abroad by tedious Travels, dangerous Sickneſſe, and perverſe Enemies, after ſo many Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there to deſert, and provocations here to relinguiſh his Religion, in that he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to us his Subjects in the ſafety both of his Perſon and Profeſſion, is a great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Secondly, It ſignifieth to <hi>Reſtore,</hi> and ſo it is Tranſlated here: Had he been but all theſe years in his Travels, his return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſafety had been matter of great joy; but it is not a ſimple Returning, but a Reſtoring, he is reſtored to his Crowns, his Kingdoms, his Revenues, and to all his <hi>Jura Regalia,</hi> after he had been ſo many years moſt unjuſtly and inhumanely outted of them, Is not this a ſignal Mercy! Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It ſignifieth to <hi>Give,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.3. And the Tranſlation would not be wide of the ſcope of Gods Spirit, if it ſhould run thus, <hi>I will give Judges as at the firſt, &amp;c.</hi> Indeed in this ſenſe we have got our King again, he is a free giſt from God, and his reſtoring an act of free Grace, and not of merit on our part: But upon the contrary, the ſins of theſe Lands cryed for continuance of bondage, and increaſe of Brick, rather then any eaſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance by his Majeſties Reſtauration, and in this God hath in part fulfilled, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49068:38"/>
                     <hi>I will love them freely,</hi> His mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe herein being moſt free. Fourthly, The word ſignifieth to <hi>Anſwer, Numb.</hi> 22.8. And this alſo diſplayeth yet a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Mercy; For his Return is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, And to what? Even to the Prayers of both the Kings, and all their Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: To the late King his Devote, his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Supplications which ye may read in his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: to his preſent Majeſties prayers, <hi>That God would ſubdue his people under him, and ſcatter the people who delight in Warre:</hi> To the prayers of all his Loyal Subjects, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands within theſe three Kingdomes dayly ſupplicating the Throne of Grace, both a part by themſelves, and joyntly with others in private Faſts for this: Which ſince God hath brought to paſſe, we ought to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a moſt gracious and comfortable return of prayer, both to our Kings and to us. Laſtly, It ſignifieth to Dwell and Reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.36. As it were, ſaith <hi>Buxtorf,</hi> derived from <hi>Jaſhav,</hi> this being the ſignification, the Tranſlation would run, <hi>I will make your Judges to reſt or dwell as at firſt, &amp;c.</hi> This I hope ſhall be the lot of his Majeſtie; His coming home being not only a Reſtauration, but a long, proſperous and peaceable ſettlement of him on his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49068:39"/>Throne, in deſpight of all his enemies, and moſt deſperate unfriends; that as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath been toſſed by the wayes of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, in a rouch and dangerous Ocean of Rebellion; ſo likewiſe in time coming, we may hope that he ſhall Live and Raign in <hi>Peace,</hi> ſince the pillars of his Throne are Religion and Righteouſneſſe, which are the ſtrong Supporters of Royal Soveraignty and Greatneſſe.</p>
                  <p>But to look upon it yet a little further, which way ſoever you caſt your eyes, you ſhall finde a Beam of Mercy breaking out therefrom: Look to the King himſelf, and the Royal Family, their toſſings abroad, their troubles at home, and the tumults of the people againſt his Majeſty, Had he not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſay, <hi>The floods have lifted up their voice, the floods have lifted up their voice:</hi> The floods of popular Inſurrection, the voice of unnatural Rebellion, that god hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him from all theſe, and let him ſee that the Lord on high is mightier then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, having ſo ſtilled theſe clamours, that they dare not utter now one ſyllable of that which of late they belched ont moſt inſolently, and liberally, and hath capacitat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to command Juſtice to have her courſe, againſt theſe Monſters of men, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49068:39"/>reproach of Chriſtianity, who moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly murthered his Royal Father: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath given him liberty to go to the Houſe of God, and ſolemnly Worſhip the God of his Fathers, after that way which the people among whom he hath ſo long ſojourned, counted Hereſie: O how much of mercy is here! redounding to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
                  <p>Look to the Church, and you ſhall ſee a Beam of Mercy breaking out likewiſe to her? What was our Church theſe many years by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone? Was it not like to become an <hi>Africa</hi> of monſtroſeties: he was thought a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of no account, that had not his Religion of a new cut. Changes of Religion was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ordinary, as faſhions in Apparel; but now we have ſo careful a nurſing Father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.16. that as he is by his place, <hi>cuſtos utriuſque tabulae;</hi> So we truſt with good <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> he will cauſe teach the Law of the Lord his God, throughout all his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, not meerly upon a politick account, becauſe (as ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) <hi>Religio &amp; ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor Dei ſolus eſt qui hominum inter ſe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ſocietatem,</hi> but upon a divine, Becauſe (as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23.) Kings are required to be Nurſing Fathers to the Church and Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for our good, as well Sacred as Civil.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49068:40"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, Look upon the Publick and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of the Kingdomes, and behold a new Ray of Mercy appear: The Ancient fundamental model of Government being altered, the Door of Diviſion and Bloody War was opened, every year of late afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us a new form of Government, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment being as unconſtant as to its form, as the Moon, and as to the Management thereof, like to a young Heretrix, every year raviſhed by the ſtrongeſt Sword, both which portended our utter ruine, <hi>For a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, cannot ſtand.</hi> And here alſo was opened a door to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Juſtice and Equity were like to the Levite and his Concubine at <hi>Gibeah,</hi> who could get no lodging. That then the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Government is ſettled upon its right <hi>baſis,</hi> ſhuteth the door upon all theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Look to the private Intereſt of perſons: Was not there deſigns like the earth to <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of mens Patrimonies and Portions, ready to ſwallow them up with a great pretence of Liberty to the Subject, and indeed they brought about a Liberty to him; But judge you what that was, Even to deliver up to them with his own hand, that which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49068:40"/>otherwiſe they would have violently taken away; ſo that men were cheated in their Eſtates, and complemented to utter ruine and miſery: Doth not here then a Beam of Mercy clearly break out? that men may challenge for their own, what is juſtly theirs, and ſit quietly under <hi>their own figtree.</hi> All this we owe to his Majeſties happy Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo that in him all publike Intereſts are wrapped up, as well Religious and Civil, as of every private man in particular; not only as to reſtitution, but alſo as to preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. When news came to <hi>Rome</hi> of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus</hi> his deſperate ſickneſſe (ſaith <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>) it ſtruke them all to the heart; but ſo ſoon as the contrary report arrived of his recovery, all people run to the Capitol, Men Women and Children, and filled the City with Acclamations of joy, crying out, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va Civitas, ſalva Patria, ſalvus Germanicus.</hi> The certainty of his Majeſties happy return, giveth us occaſion of the like joyful Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and hereupon may we truely ſay, <hi>Salva Civitas, ſalva Patria,</hi> yea more, <hi>ſalva Eccleſia, ſalvus Carolus,</hi> the City is ſafe, the Country is ſafe, the Church is ſafe, King <hi>Charles</hi> is ſafe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 2.</hi> This ſerveth to reprove ſuch, who what ever they ſay, look upon our Kings
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49068:41"/>Reſtauration as no Mercy: And however, I diſapprove their judgement with abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, yet I muſt commend their wit (if not their aſtoniſhment) which command them ſilence; for in this, they prudently imitate the ſilly Crans, who flying over Mount <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> taketh each of them a Peeble-ſtone in his mouth to withhold their chattering, leſt the Eagles ſhould hear and make prey of them: remembering as might ſeem what was ſaid to King <hi>Philip, Domine Philippe ubique ſanè ades, &amp; undequaque vides, omniaque auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult as apud Atheninſes verò Potiſſimum. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> our Lord, thou art every where preſent, thou ſeeth every where, and heareth all things, but moſt eſpecially among the <hi>Atheniens,</hi> which with little alteration, may be as well applied to moſt of Kings; ſo that it were far better for them, together with the Arms of that Bloody Commonwealth, (now fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ground) to pull down and reject their baſe <hi>Antimonarchical</hi> principles, and bury them in the Rubbiſh of their fallen <hi>Babel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. The ſurrounding of a reſtored King with pious and prudent Counſellours, is a great mercy; for this tendeth both to the proſperity of the King, and the felicity of his Kingdome: This promiſe in theſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49068:41"/>words maketh the truth manifeſt, and the wiſeſt Monarchs we read of in holy Scripture, have ſtudied to have ſuch about them: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had his <hi>Huſhai,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> his Old, Wiſe, Sage States-men, who gave good counſel to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> had he been ſo happy as to have followed it, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus</hi> had ſeven who <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.14. are called his Counſellours: And <hi>Eſther</hi> 1.14. you have all their names mentioned, Great Affairs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire deep conſultations, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nius mens non eſt capax tantae molis,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi>) And therefore it is, that Kings have both their publike and private Councels, which they call together, <hi>propter ardua Regni,</hi> for to aſſiſt them in hard and difficult Points and Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencies in Government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. It is God alone who raiſeth and reſtoreth a fallen and lapſed Magiſtrate: It was he that brought <hi>David</hi> back again over <hi>Jordan,</hi> and reſtored <hi>Mannaſſeh</hi> to his Throne, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to his wonted greatneſſe, <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes decree Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Prov.</hi> 8.15. For confirmation hereof, take theſe following reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, He, and He alone, hath right ſo to do: God is Judge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.7. And to him it was that <hi>David</hi> went for redreſſe in his baniſhment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>For thou, O
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49068:42"/>Lord, art the lifter up of my head,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting and defending of baniſhed Princes, (which the Emperour thinketh to be his priviledge) this God doth perform upon an unqueſtionable title, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Salvation belongeth to the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, As he hath the Right, ſo he hath the Power: A man may have the Right, but not the Power to execute the ſame: <hi>Aliud jus ad rem, atqui aliud jus in re:</hi> It is not ſo with God, the right he hath, is accompanied with power, to put the ſame in execution: As, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.10. <hi>My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is of God who ſaveth the upright in heart:</hi> And hence he is called, <hi>The mighty God, the Almighty:</hi> When his Vicegerent is ſtripped naked of Moaſts and Armies, he can raiſe up Armies for his Service, or ſend the Spirit of Diviſion amongſt the Enemies of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, He hath not only Power, but Valour: Valour is required to ſo high an Atchievement as this, otherwiſe both Right and power may fail in accompliſhing their deſtinate end, This Attribute the Lord asketh to be his own, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.3. <hi>The Lord is a man of War, Jehovah is his Name:</hi> He is the tenth Worthy that never fled in Batttel, and all the other nine that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49068:42"/>Hiſtories mention, come far, far ſhort of him in this.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, As he hath Right, Power, and Valour, ſo likewiſe hath he good Conduct, he is both Vigilant, Diligent, and Prudent, <hi>Dux autem eſto, qui tum ea quae ante ipſum, tum quae à tergo ſunt proſpiciat:</hi> Saith one, He only is fit to be a General, who can ſee round about him, that is, who hath proweſs and skill to lead and conduct his Army, and God is eminently ſuch a one; He can order all things ſo fitly for the work, as is wonderful to think upon, find out the materials and joyn them (like ſo many pieces of timber in ſome Elaborate Artifice, by a wiſe and cunning <hi>Mechanick</hi>) in the Arte of His Holy and Wiſe Providence; He hath ſuch intelligence of his enemy, as he exactly knoweth what is a doing in his Camp, <hi>2 King.</hi> 6.8. He can go unto his enemies Camp, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> to <hi>Abners,</hi> taking <hi>Sauls</hi> Spear, and can either ſnatch the weapons out of the hands of his enemies, or ſo blunt them as they cannot hurt; yea, he can go unto the enemies hearts, and as the rivers of water turn their rebellious projects into the channels of loyalty and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This Doctrine (as the hand of a Dyal) pointeth at the Author of this happy
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49068:43"/>Revolution, wherewith we are bleſſed: that is our gracious and good God who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored our King, and ſet him upon the Throns of his Fathers, by which he hath manifeſted much both of Wiſdom, and Goodneſſe: of Wiſedome, in that he hath indued him with ſuch rare Virtues, both Chriſtian and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they have been as a Loadſtone to draw his peoples hearts unto him. Of his Goodneſſe, which he hath moſt ſignally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, in making the people ſo univerſally to eye, and truely to admire, thoſe ſhyning Virtues in his Royal Perſon, that even in the loweſt ebb of his Majeſties Affairs, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Eclipſe of his Greatneſſe, no object could interpoſe it ſelf, betwixt their thoughts and him, to areaſt them from admiring his richly adorned Perſon, although denuded of all that Stately Pomp and Magnifick Acutriment that uſually accompany princes. As for the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Graces wherewith the Lord indued him the moſt ſingular and eminent, amongſt them are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> where of in all his Travels abroad, the Proteſtant Churches were earneſt and ſerious beholders, and now are unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous witneſſes in giving teſtimony thereof. And hath not he made good this at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, in accompliſhing <hi>Davids</hi> promiſe in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49068:43"/>his affliction (which doubtleſſe he made his own) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43.4. Giving thanks to God, even the God of his joy and gladneſſe, for the Lords remembering of him in the day of his low condition: as he had during that time been much in ſupplication for the ſame, ſo he hath ſolemnly dedicated his Government to the moſt High, by a ſevere, yet juſt act againſt profanneſſe, like <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 101.3. He <hi>will ſet no wicked thing before his eyes, hating the works of theſe who fall away to ſin.</hi> This is now the incenſe he burneth, which ſmelleth ſweetly in Gods noſtrils.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Virtue is, <hi>Conſtancy in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Reformed Religion,</hi> by which he ſtandeth, not only a mirrour to all his own Subjects at home, but alſo to all Proteſtant Princes, and Profeſſors thereof abroad, like an immovable rock amidſt the waves of reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated aſſaults, which his greateſt Adverſaries and moſt ſevere Cenſurers (the Changlings of the Times) had never been able to have withſtood; but certainly would, if they could have found out a way, have hazarded their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Crown of Glory, rather then not to have had one pull at theſe three Crowns of his, if they could have pretended the leaſt intereſt in them, although they ſhould have ſweamed to them, through a Sea of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49068:44"/>Chriſtian bloud; but he chooſed with <hi>Moſes</hi> to wave all worldly advantages rather, then by the change of his Religion to hazard eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory.</p>
                  <p>His third Chriſtian Virtue, is, <hi>Patience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the croſſe,</hi> wherein he ſhined moſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly; for howbeit he was born the Heir of three Mighty Kingdomes, of ſo Royal and Ancient Extraction, that the Chriſtian World is not able to afford his parallel, and had edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſuitable to his birth, being brought up in Scarlet with all that tenderneſſe faithful Subjects could pay to ſo hopeful a Prince, under whoſe ſhaddow the ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might hope to inherit her earthly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; yet behold how humbly he taketh up, and with what patience he ſuſtaineth the croſſe, ſo that <hi>Jobs</hi> patience and <hi>Davids</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility were never ſo nighly matched by any, as by himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Followeth his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Virtues,<note place="margin">Spes certa quiet is &amp; ſalutis perfecta in gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatore ſapientia: pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, cujus Magiſter ad clavi regimen intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus dote praeparatur, ubi que ſtationem, ubique portum habet in flucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Ennodius.</note> among which his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> doth merit to be reckoned in the firſt place; of which he hath ſo large a portion, that this Kingdom dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſhort time of his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49068:44"/>amongſt us, did behold his deportment with ſuch pleaſure and delight, as that they looked upon it as a morning, which ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with a noontide of a happy and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Government: nothing ſhort of that of his Royal Grand-father, the wiſeſt (if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out arrogancy we may ſpeak it) of Chriſtian Princes: neither was this only our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, for whilſt he ſojourned amongſt Forrainers, he was looked upon as a Patern to their ableſt Statiſts, in their greateſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions; of a moſt ſtayed and ſolide judgment, which is an induement exceeding well becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a perſonage, and very neceſſary to a Prince: for <hi>Omnibus animalibus, faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius eſt, quam hominibus, imperare:</hi> It is more eaſie to exerce dominion over all other creatures, then to govern man.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> With what undaunted courage hath he born the revilings of his enemies? therein he was nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> or <hi>Tiberius</hi> the greateſt Emperours on earth; wherein he chuſed for himſelf the beſt of Paterns, the example of the King of Saints now in Heaven, who moſt magnanimouſly deſpiſed all the contempt and reproaches of baſe, perverſe, and treacherous men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3.5. and forward.</p>
                  <p>The third Princely Vertue is his <hi>Clemency,</hi>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49068:45"/>In which Vertue Kings reſemble much their Maker (and it is no diſparagement for them ſo to do) who glorieth to be <hi>ſlow to anger, and ready to forgive;</hi> and in this there no King in the world cometh ſo near to God, as his Majeſties ſelf; which was moſt reſplendent in the time of his affliction, by the frequent of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of Acts of Indempnity to his Enemies: And of late alſo, he being ſo ready to forgive Enemies, that none was more forward to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor he free and ready to grant pardon: Like unto <hi>Marcus Barbaricus</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> who being queſtioned why he was ſo ſlow to puniſh injuries, anſwered, <hi>Boni principis eſt non ſe ulciſci de inimicis, ſed ſufficit ut ſe ulciſci poſſe declaret.</hi> A good King will not delight ſo much in avenging of himſelf on his Enemies, as in declaring and making notare to the world, that he can and may be avenged upon them.</p>
                  <p>The laſt is his <hi>Valour,</hi> Wherein no Prince in Chriſtendome can outvy him, which having been often put to the Teſt, both at Home and Abroad was found current coyn; for it proved <hi>Ariadnes</hi> threed to himſelf and his friends many times, when they knew not what to ſay or do, <hi>Ad fremitus habuit qui corda invicta Leonis.</hi> He had alwayes the heart of a Lion when he was in the labyrinth of greateſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49068:45"/>hazards. <hi>Seneca</hi> his definition of a King <hi>(Rex eſt qui metuit nihil. A King is one who feareth nothing)</hi> is the very portrait of the Kings Majeſty; which is a happy <hi>Omen</hi> of our following proſperity and peace: For, ſaith <hi>Ardobrandinus, imperii tutela fidiſſima forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo: Fortitude is the beſt guardian of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was the great Wiſedome of God that adorned his Royal Perſon with ſo many choice Vertues, and made them ſhine in ſuch luſter in him, who was a Prince born to ſo many troubles; for had he been no better furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then ordinary Princes are, he could not have been obſerved and remarked by people under ſuch a dark cloud. 2. The Lords goodneſſe appeareth in turning all peoples hearts and eyes towards him: as his Wiſdom fitted the Object for the Organ, his Perſon for their obſervation, ſo his Goodneſſe diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Organs for obſerving and beholding the object; for though his Chriſtian and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vertues were ſtrong Loadſtones, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peoples eyes were purblind through fear, and others blind through faction, which, till God cured them by a <hi>collyrium</hi> and eye-ſalve of his own compounding, were unfit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. But when theſe ſcales were removed they (with the reſt of his Loyal Subjects)
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49068:46"/>beheld him as a heaven (though upon earth) richly beſpangled with many fixed Stars of Grace and Vertue; the influence; of which produced (before they were aware) a myne of Loyalty in their breaſts. It ſeemeth his Royal Father did forſee this; for in his thoughts to the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> he aſſerteth, <hi>That the Mountains of congealed Faction ſhall by the sunſhine of Gods Mercy, and the ſplendor of his Vertues, be thawed and diſſipated.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But his Wiſdom and his Goodneſſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yet further, in that it was done ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, the means by which the ſame were performed having no aptneſſe for, yea, much averſneſſe from, that happy Work: and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to me it ſeemeth the juſt parallel of Chriſts curing the blind man with laying upon his eyes <hi>clay and ſpittle,</hi> which were ready to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but no wayes apt to help the fight: That Army that did the work, had as real an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy therewith, in the very ſame time they were ignorantly doing it, as at any time before; ſo that God in this wonderfully fulfilled <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle, bringing <hi>meat out of the eater, and ſweetneſſe out of the ſtrong,</hi> the meat of Peace, and the ſweetneſſe of Truth, and in this God gave a daſh to the fooliſh opinion, concerning Religious qualification of Armies, and proclaimeth himſelf to be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49068:46"/>
                     <hi>JEHOVAH, whoſe right hand doth ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, His Wiſdom and his Goodneſſe appeareth in the peaceable carrying through thereof, without the roaring of Canons, the devaſtation of Countries, the razing of Cities, the effuſion of Blood, to all which he have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been provoked by unparallelled injuries done to his Royal Father, his own Perſon, Authority and Family: that this <hi>Epidemick</hi> madneſſe ſhould have been cured without phlebotomie and ſtrong purgatives, ſhoweth a twiſting together, both of Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Wiſedome in the diſpenſation, and is a Prognoſtick (it being ſo like the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple) that he ſhall be another <hi>Solomon,</hi> Who, becauſe not a man of bloud, was fitted for the building of the Houſe of the Lord his God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, His Goodneſſe and Wiſdom ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in that it was ſo unexpected, after ſo many diſappointments, ſo many deſigns blown up, ſo many aſſayes fruſtrate, when ſo many adventures had proven as <hi>the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloud,</hi> that few exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed any to have the Spirit and Courage to give it an other hazard: Even then (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, God unexpectedly appearing) did the Good and Wiſe Hand of Providence begin
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49068:47"/>to work, when all men had given over to think of our coming out from miſery, and his return to the dignity of his Anceſtours: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Homer.</hi> But <hi>the things which are impoſſible with men, are poſſible with God, Luk.</hi> 18.27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. As the firſt uſe pointed at the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Deliverance, ſo this at the duty of the Delivered. And firſt, it diſcovereth the duty of the King, and it is thankfulneſs to his God that hath done all theſe things for him: to him are his Vows to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.1. Would to God his Subjects made as good uſe of the Mercy, as our Gracious Soveraign doth. Secondly, It diſcovereth the duty of the Subjects whoſe it is to rejoyce in God, ſince he is the doer hereof, and not with a common and ordinary joy, for this is not a common and ordinary mercy. I would have you for ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating of this affection, and putting it right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in tune, take theſe three <hi>Directions.</hi> Firſt, Let your joy be ſuitable, though it cannot be proportionable, to the nature of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. People that have been ſome years at Sea, and have met with ſtrange Tempeſts, and croſſe Tydes, and have been every day in jeopardy of their Lives, once come to their hoped-for Harbour, how exceedingly do they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49068:47"/>rejoyce and delight therein? becauſe it puts them out of fear of being ſwallowed up with the ſwelling ſurges of the unmerciful Ocean. We have been toſſed theſe many years paſt, in a worſe and more dangerous Sea, then ever Ship did ſail upon, the winde <hi>Euroclydon</hi> having vexed us, and that in the midſt of Rocks and contrary Tydes, from which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in his Majeſties Reſtauration, we have obtained deliverance; ſo that the prayer of his late Majeſty, in his counſel to his Son (<hi>My Prayer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to God Almighty, is, that whatever cometh of me, who am wrapt up in my own innocency and his Grace, that he would be pleaſed to make you an Anchor or Harbour rather to theſe toſſed and weather-beaten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi>) hath been heard in heaven: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is the Harbour theſe Kingdoms have happily at length arrived at, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth immunity from death, threatnings, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and well may it be called as that place <hi>Paul</hi> ſailed by, <hi>Act.</hi> 27.28. the <hi>fair havens,</hi> and not only ſo, but the <hi>ſure havens</hi> alſo, for none elſe could have afforded us ſuch ſafety. Have we not reaſon then to rejoyce in the God of our Salvation, and cry out, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O Lord, do we give thanks, for that thy Name is near thy wondrous works declare,</hi> and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> joyfully to ſhout aloud, <hi>GOD SAVE
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49068:48"/>THE KING,</hi> ſince in him, by the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Wiſdome of God; we are ſaved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Direct.</hi> 2. As our Joy would be ſuitable, ſo it would be ſpotleſſe, a virgin pure joy, far from the pollution of exceſſe: I ſhall give you theſe following Preſervatives againſt the infection of this ſin</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The very Heathens have called and accounted it a madneſſe, <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who was an Heathen Philoſopher, calls it <hi>voluntaria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſania,</hi> a voluntary madneſſe; If heathens then that wanted the light of the Word from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and the light of a renued conſcience from within, who weighed all things but in the ſcales of reaſon, and accordingly judged of them, did ſo look upon this ſin; what ſhould Chriſtians do, who, beſide reaſon, have the light of Gods Word, and the dictats of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued conſcience, to direct them? I pray you go not mad both againſt Reaſon, Scripture and Conſcience: <hi>A threefold cord is not eaſily broken,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> a threefold agravation of ſin, is a threefold cord binding the guilt upon men, What ſpeaketh this to you, but to ſtear of this Rock?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Conſider, You are Subjects to the King of Kings, as well as to your Dear and Dread Soveraign the Kings Majeſty; for in this, as you will teſtifie nothing of your
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49068:48"/>Loyaltie to your Soveraign on Earth; ſo hereby you ſhall declare much diſloyaltie to your Soveraign in Heaven: As you cannot hereby demonſtrate your ſelves good Subjects; for the greateſt Traitor may ſymbolize in this with you, and go as far as he that is ſtrongeſt to wreſtle in theſe ſhameful <hi>Olympicks;</hi> ſo you evidently proclaim you are not good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: Let the remembrance hereof be a bridle to your deſires, leſt your exultation be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a provocation.</p>
                  <p>The third Preſervative is, To remember for what end God hath wrought this Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of us, and hath reſtored our King to his Subjects; is it not, that we may live a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peaceable life under him? ſure it is; and we cannot live a godly life, if we live ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually like beaſts, God hath not delivered us that we ſhould abuſe his creatures, miſpend time, and beaſt our ſelves, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.15, 16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Direct.</hi> 3. Let this our joy be conſtant, not a flaſh, like the ſudden motion of lightning in the Air, but a continued and laſting rejoycing, the ſpirits and life that runneth in the veins and arteries of all the duties we owe to our King, making us to perform them conſtantly, joyfully, and chearfully. They muſt not be preſented, as ſome Ancients complained the benefits they received were, <hi>viſcata beneficia,</hi> benefits that hing to the fingers of thoſe who
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49068:49"/>give them like Bird-lime: but let our duties be the offerings of free hearts: If it happen that his Majeſties Affairs ſhould call from us for ſome of our means, let us anſwer chearfully and give with joy; Some years ago, gladly would we have had the occaſion of doing it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> laſt, <hi>It is the Lord that raiſeth Kings, and reſtoreth to their wonted Honours and Priviledges, Noble, Wiſe and Faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours.</hi> It was Gods wiſe Providence brought <hi>Joſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and <hi>Moredcai</hi> to <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> and holy and wiſe <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Darius,</hi> it is the Lords hand that bringeth out from under the cloud of reſtraint and violence, to their wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Honour and Priviledges, the Councels and Repreſentatives of Kingdomes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This again giveth us matter of praiſe, that God having reſtored our King as at firſt, ſo he is in a way of reſtoring our Counſellours as at the beginning, ſetting over us men of our own Nation and Blood, men of Honour, Prudence, and Conſcience (<hi>Tales ſunt praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Regni, non exercitus non The ſauri;</hi> Such, not Treaſures nor Armies, are the ſtrength and defence of a Kingdom) to ſit at the Helm of Affairs, and ſweept away the Strangers that abode in the Cities of our Solemnities, as Cobwebs in our neateſt Rooms, ſtaining all our Glory, the product of the poyſonous Spiders that had creept in unto the Palaces
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49068:49"/>of our King, and alſo reſtoring our Publike Councels, the High Courts of Parliament in theſe Kingdoms to their wonted and ancient Priviledges: Thoſe many years by paſt, the Parliaments of theſe Kingdoms have been very Monſters, an <hi>omnigadarum</hi> of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, without Head and Shoulders, a model not heard of before amongſt us: and the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental mould of Parliaments, according to the Laws of the reſpective Kingdomes, hath been quite out of faſhion; yea, Courts of that kind have been like the <hi>Samaritan</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> lying deadly wounded, or rather like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Lord and Maſter, both dead and buried. Now the Lord is preparing for their Reſurrection, and as he did to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inviteth them in the preſence of our King, and the countenance of his Royal Authority, to ariſe and come out from the grave of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in which they have been long impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Lord make them, and the whole Land with them, to remember both their Deliverer and Deliverance, that what <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> held for an unqueſtionble truth <hi>(there was nothing ſo ſoon forgot as a benefit received)</hi> may be found a lie both as to them and us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> laſt, Let us pray, ſince God is reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Counſellours as at the beginning, that he would give them alſo Wiſdom and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49068:50"/>the fear of His Name, that the King may be happy in their Councels, as they are happy in a Gracious and moſt Wiſe King. And ſince God is giving to <hi>Ceſar what is Ceſars,</hi> and to them what is theirs, that both may <hi>give to God what is Gods:</hi> the freſh remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Uſurpation on themſelves, warning them not to incroach upon him: That all <hi>theſe who have ſown in tears may reap in joy:</hi> That our King may be eſtabliſhed for ever upon the Throns of his Royal Anceſtors: for which I ſhall (and I hope, without hazard of accuſation I may) turn the promiſe made to <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 89.20. in a prayer for him; <hi>O Lord, as thou haſt found</hi> King Charles <hi>thy Servant, and with holy oyl haſt anointed him, ſo let thy hand hold him faſt: and thy arm ſtrengthen him. Let never his enemies be able to oppreſse him; nor the ſon of wickedneſse any more to hurt him: but ſmite down his foes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his face, and plague them that hate him. Let thy truth and mercy be with him, and in thy Name exalt his horn:</hi> So be it, even ſo be it, O Lord. To this Lord, who is able to perform all theſe, even to our God, who hath <hi>reſtored our Judges as at firſt, and our Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours as at the beginning, and hath purged out the tinne and the droſſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> be praiſe, glory and honour, for now and ever. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:50"/>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49068:51"/>
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> p. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> r. ſickneſs. line laſt, <hi>for</hi> ever, <hi>read</hi> alſo.</p>
                  <p>Page <hi>12.</hi> line <hi>3, 4. for Prov. 24, 21.</hi> read, <hi>1 Pet. 2.17.</hi> p. <hi>20.</hi> l. <hi>12. for</hi> debauching, r. demeaning. p. <hi>26.</hi> l. <hi>25.</hi> r. concomitant, p. <hi>34.</hi> l. <hi>26.</hi> he looketh, r. they look. p. <hi>38.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> their r. his. p. <hi>43.</hi> l. <hi>8.</hi> unto, r. into, p. <hi>45.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> r. inadvertency, p. <hi>46.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> unto, r. in, p. <hi>47.</hi> l. <hi>ult.</hi> hath, r. have, p. <hi>53.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> r. reſtore, p. <hi>57.</hi> l. <hi>11.</hi> r. timpany p. <hi>66.</hi> l. <hi>19.</hi> of, r. off, p. <hi>78.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> her, r. their. p. <hi>85.</hi> l. <hi>20.</hi> r. death-threatning, p. <hi>88.</hi> l. <hi>7. del.</hi> Kings. p. <hi>89.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> r. omnigatherum.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
